<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?><document><header> <!-- <meta content="HTML Tidy, see www.w3.org" name="generator"/> --> <title>Obtain the Apache Forrest distribution</title></header><body><section id="how"><title id="how">How to download</title><p class="note">Please realise that Forrest is still pre-1.0 release version. It is certainly usable for those who are prepared to move with it. See more notes about <link href="index.html#status">status</link>.</p><p>Use the links below to download a distribution of Apache Forrest from one of our mirrors. It is good practice to <link href="[location]#verify">verify the integrity</link> of the distribution files.</p><p>Apache Forrest is distributed as a <code>zip</code> archive (for Windows) and as a <code>tar.gz</code> archive (for UNIX). The contents are the same, the only difference is the line-endings of all text files.</p><p>The distribution contains all of the source code, documentation, and resources, together with the pre-built ready-to-run forrest binary.</p></section><section id="closest"><title id="closest">Current official release (closest mirror site selected automatically)</title><p>You are currently using <strong>[preferred]</strong>. If you encounter a problem with this mirror, then please select another. If all mirrors are failing, there are backup mirrors at the end of the list. See <link href="http://www.apache.org/mirrors/">status</link> of mirrors.</p><form id="SelectMirror" method="get" action="[location]">Other mirrors: <select name="Preferred"><!--[if-any http] [for http]--><option value="[http]">[http]</option><!--[end] [end]--><!--[if-any ftp] [for ftp]--><option value="[ftp]">[ftp]</option><!--[end] [end]--><!--[if-any backup] [for backup]--><option value="[backup]">[backup] (backup)</option><!--[end] [end]--></select> <input value="Change" type="submit"/></form><p>The current release is Apache Forrest 0.7 (see the <link href="[preferred]/forrest/RELEASE-NOTES-0.7.txt">release notes</link>).</p><ul><li>For UNIX operating systems: <link href="[preferred]/forrest/apache-forrest-0.7.tar.gz">apache-forrest-0.7.tar.gz</link> [<link href="http://www.apache.org/dist/forrest/apache-forrest-0.7.tar.gz.asc">PGP</link>] [<link href="http://www.apache.org/dist/forrest/apache-forrest-0.7.tar.gz.md5">MD5</link>]</li><li>For Windows operating systems: <link href="[preferred]/forrest/apache-forrest-0.7.zip">apache-forrest-0.7.zip</link> [<link href="http://www.apache.org/dist/forrest/apache-forrest-0.7.zip.asc">PGP</link>] [<link href="http://www.apache.org/dist/forrest/apache-forrest-0.7.zip.md5">MD5</link>]</li></ul></section><section id="svn"><title id="svn">Snapshots of current development and head SVN repository</title><p>If you want to use the latest Apache Forrest features, the source code is under version control with Subversion (read how to <link href="site:documentation/developers/build">obtain</link> your working copy). There are also compressed source <link href="http://svn.apache.org/snapshots/forrest/">snapshots</link> that are packed every 6 hours.</p></section><section id="archive"><title id="archive">Archive of old releases</title><p>Older releases are available in the <link href="http://archive.apache.org/dist/forrest/">archive</link>. Those releases are only provided as historical artefacts. We strongly recommend to not use those releases, but upgrade to the most recent release.</p></section><section id="verify"><title id="verify">Verify releases</title><p>It is essential that you verify the integrity of the downloaded files using the PGP and MD5 signatures. MD5 verification ensures the file was not corrupted during the download process. PGP verification ensures that the file came from a certain person.</p><p>The PGP signatures can be verified using <link href="http://www.pgpi.org/">PGP</link> or <link href="http://www.gnupg.org/">GPG</link>. First download the Apache Forrest <link href="http://svn.apache.org/repos/asf/forrest/trunk/KEYS">KEYS</link> as well as the <code>asc</code> signature file for the particular distribution. It is important that you get these files from the ultimate trusted source - the main ASF distribution site, rather than from a mirror. Then verify the signatures using ...</p><pre>% pgpk -a KEYS
% pgpv apache-forrest-X.Y.tar.gz.asc

<em>or</em>

% pgp -ka KEYS
% pgp apache-forrest-X.Y.tar.gz.asc

<em>or</em>

% gpg --import KEYS
% gpg --verify apache-forrest-X.Y.tar.gz.asc
</pre><p>To verify the MD5 signature on the files, you need to use a program called <code>md5</code> or <code>md5sum</code>, which is included in many unix distributions. It is also available as part of <link href="http://www.gnu.org/software/textutils/textutils.html">GNU Textutils</link>. Windows users can get binary md5 programs from <link href="http://www.fourmilab.ch/md5/">here</link>, <link href="http://www.pc-tools.net/win32/freeware/console/">here</link>, or <link href="http://www.slavasoft.com/fsum/">here</link>.</p><p>We strongly recommend you verify your downloads with both PGP and MD5.</p></section></body></document>