<?xml version="1.0"?>
<project name="Apache Forrest">
  <info module="xml-forrest" 
        packages="org.apache.forrest.*" 
        version="0.1" 
        tag="dev" 
        year="2002" 
        web="http://xml.apache.org/forrest/">
    <mailing-lists>    
     <mailing-list target="developer" 
                   mail="forrest-dev@xml.apache.org" 
                   subscribe="forrest-dev-subscribe@xml.apache.org" 
                   unsubscribe="forrest-dev-unsubscribe@xml.apache.org"/>    
   </mailing-lists>    
  </info>
  <description>
    <short>Forrest wants to provide a good technological infrastructure for open 
           software development for the Apache Software Foundation based on ASF 
           software, ASF practices and experience and modern software design 
           principles.</short>
    <detailed>Ever seen 'sourceforge'? ok, than you know what a technological 
              insfrastructure for open development is. Ever seen Mozilla's
              'tinkerbox' and 'bonsai'? ok, then you know what we mean for
              'helping tools'. Take all the wishes/dreams that you ever had 
              when you were participating in an OSS community... well, we 
              want Forrest to make them possible.
    </detailed>
    <why>If you ever participated in ASF open development you know why: there is 
         always the feeling that you are left on your own, that each project, effort, 
         community mail list and invidual has to struggle to keep up with the others 
         and to keep coherence. This effort was started by those who believe that a 
         better and more coherent technical infrastructure is a first step in the 
         right direction.</why>
  </description>
  <requirements>Centipede, Ant, Cocoon, Java 1.2</requirements>  
  <developers>
    <!-- in strict alphabetical order -->
    <person name="David Crossley" email="crossley@apache.org" id="DC"/>
    <person name="Stefano Mazzocchi" email="stefano@apache.org" id="SM"/>
    <person name="John Morrison" email="morrijr@apache.org" id="JM"/>
    <person name="Steven Noels" email="stevenn@apache.org" id="SN"/>
    <person name="Sam Ruby" email="rubys@apache.org" id="RS"/>
    <person name="Volunteer needed" email="forrest-dev@xml.apache.org" id="open"/>    
  </developers>
  <goals>
    <goal>publishing system for documentation </goal>
    <goal>a build system for code</goal>
    <goal>analysis of logs and publishing of results </goal>
  </goals>
  <todo>
   <actions priority="high">
    <action context="code" assigned-to="open">
     Merge Gump DTDs and work on them. We have to standardize the work on 
     the rest of the DTDs that will be required by Forrest.
    </action>
    <action context="code" assigned-to="open">
     Ensure solid XML infrastructure. At least the initial XML instances
     (e.g. changes.xml and todo.xml) need to validate using external tools.
    </action>
   </actions>
  </todo>
  <changes>
   <release version="0.1" date="2002">
    <action dev="SN" type="add">
     Imported Centipede as a build system.
    </action>
    <action dev="DC" type="update" due-to="Steven Noels" due-to-email="stevenn@outerthought.org">
     Ensure that initial DTDs are valid and that the initial XML instances can be
     validated using these DTDs and OASIS Catalogs.
    </action>
    <action dev="SM" type="add">
     Initial Import
    </action>
   </release>
  </changes>  
  <licence>This software is released under the Apache Public License 1.1. 
           For detailed legal and licensing issues, please read the LICENSE.* files
           in the /legal directory.
  </licence>
  <credits>
    <credit>This product includes software developed by the Krysalis Project 
            (http://www.krysalis.org/).
    </credit>
  </credits>
</project>
