<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  Copyright 2006 The Apache Software Foundation or its licensors,
  as applicable.

  Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
  you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  You may obtain a copy of the License at

      http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.
-->
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN"
  "http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">
<document>
    <header>
        <title>How to Release Forrest</title>
        <abstract>This documents the steps that the Release Manager (RM) should follow when doing a Forrest
        release.</abstract>
    </header>
    <body>

        <section id="About">
            <title>About this Document</title>
            <p>This documents the steps that the Release Manager (RM) should follow when doing a Forrest release. Note
                that it might have mistakes - we seem to discover something new each time and some steps might need to
                happen in a different order. Fine tune these notes for next time. Do some practice runs.</p>

            <p>There are some steps that other committers, and even developers, can assist with, especially in the areas
                of getting ready for the release and the final testing. Many of the steps can be done only by the
                Release Manager.</p>

            <p>It is not the Release Manager's job to fix bugs nor address blocker issues. The RM job begins when the
                project is ready to do the release.</p>

            <p>Review the "FIXME" notes below.</p>
        </section>
        <section id="Preparations">
            <title>Preparations</title>
            
            <ol>
                <li>
                    <p>The Release Manager (RM) starts the process to finalise the outstanding blocker issues. </p>
                    <p>Check and make sure the following preconditions are met:</p>
                    <ul>
                        <li>
                            <p>Has the project prepared or updated the Roadmap to schedule the realistic Issues?</p>
                        </li>
                        <li>
                            <p>Has the project made good progress towards fixing the Blockers and applying the
                                outstanding patches?</p>
                        </li>
                    </ul>
                    <p>If so send an email to get the project to decide what to do with the remaining issues. Propose to
                        delay some issues to a future release, encourage people to fix others. See <a
                            href="http://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/FOR-853"
                            >FOR-853</a>. Look at <a
                                href="http://www.mail-archive.com/dev@forrest.apache.org/msg02310.html">msg02310.html</a>
                        for an example of such a message.</p>
                    
                    <fixme>What if preconditions are not met?</fixme>
                </li>
                <li>
                    <p>Prepare the Release Plan to define the corner stones of the coming release</p>
                    
                    <ul>
                        <li>Start of code-freeze</li>
                        <li>Start of test-period</li>
                        <li>Vote on release candidate</li>
                        <li>Optional creation of release candidate #2 (when there are bugs)</li>
                        <li>Start of test-period #2</li>
                        <li>Vote on release candidate #2</li>
                        <li>Scheduled release Date</li>
                    </ul>
                    <p>Use email template <a href="propose_release_plan.txt">propose_release_plan.txt</a> to plan and
                        propose.</p>
                    
                    
                </li>
                <li>
                    <p>Call for a quick vote on the release plan on the dev list.</p>
                    <note><p>There are various reasons for voting on the Release Plan, e.g. makes people aware that a
                        code-freeze is about to happen; encourage them to get involved with the release; ensure that the
                        date is suitable and people will be around to test and then vote on the actual release. See a
                        good discussion <a href="http://marc.theaimsgroup.com/?t=114296877800003">in the archives</a> </p></note>
                </li>
            </ol>
        </section>

    </body>
</document>
