<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V1.1//EN" "document-v11.dtd">
<document> 
  <header> 
    <title>The Contract</title><authors><person name="Marc Portier" email="mpo@outerthought.org"/></authors> 
    <notice>The legal tone of this document is just a gimmick, this is not a
      legal document in any sense. At all times: since this is open source: the real
      contract is described in the implementation details of the full distribution.
      This tries to list (not explain) what the ins and outs of using forrest is
      about. Please let <link href="mailto:forrest-dev@apache.org">us</link> know if
      any of the bullets listed here are out of sync with the real
      implementation.</notice>
    <abstract>This document describes in a very techy bullet-style way how to use Forrest.</abstract> 
  </header> 
  <body> 
    <p>This document describes the formal contract between the
      <strong>Forrest distribution code</strong>, hereafter referred as Forrest, and
      the <strong>Project (team) using it for generating its documentation
      web-site</strong>, hereafter TheProject, or in the best case: You.</p><section> 
      <title>Forrest will:</title> 
      <ul> 
        <li>provide DTDs, skins, cocoon-pipelines, and a willing team of
          supporting developers at <link href="mailto:forrest-dev@apache.org">forrest-dev@apache.org</link></li> 
      <li>use Cocoon to generate the HTML documentation for TheProject</li> 
      </ul> 
    </section> 
    <section> 
      <title>TheProject Must:</title> 
      <note><code>{docroot}</code> is the location inside TheProject's file
        hierarchy where all documentation related resources are stored. Commonly,
        <code>{docroot}</code> equals to
        <code>{projecthome}/src/documentation</code></note> 
      <ul> 
        <li>provide XML content in <code>{docroot}/content/xdocs</code> using
          the forrest DTDs,</li> 
        <li>provide content navigation metadata by sliding
          <code>book.xml</code> and <code>tabs.xml</code> files in there as well.
          (Forrest is working on a libre alternative to the book.xml approach).</li> 
      <li>provide own xml project descriptor files in the directory <code>{projecthome}</code></li></ul> 
    </section> 
    <section> 
      <title>TheProject Can (accidentally):</title> 
      <warning>Use the following features at your own risk. These are only
        <em>side-effects</em> of the current implementation. Perhaps this shouldn't be
        documented at all.</warning> 
      <ul> 
        <li>provide his own skin in a directory
          <code>{docroot}/skins/{your-skin-name}</code> (check the current Forrest skins
          and the related pipelines to see what they are doing)</li> 
        <li>provide own DTDs (and stylesheets) to work with in
          <code>{docroot}/resources/schema/dtd</code> 
          <ul> 
            <li>maybe also extra required stylesheets to convert own grammar to
              'document' (being the format that the skins work on)</li> 
            <li>and probably with an updated
              <code>{docroot}/resources/schema/catalog</code></li> 
          </ul> </li> 
        <li>provide his own overwriting versions of
          <code>{docroot}/sitemap.xmap</code>, <code>{docroot}/cocoon.xconf</code> etc
          ... (be sure you know what you are doing since you're leaving the area where
          other Forresters can help you out.</li> 
      </ul> 
    </section> 
    <section> 
      <title>TheProject Cannot (currently)</title> 
      <ul> 
        <li>provide own Java classes or libraries needed in the generation
          process,</li> 
        <li>provide mountable sub-sitemaps.</li> 
      </ul> 
    </section> 
  </body>
</document>
