<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  Copyright 2002-2004 The Apache Software Foundation

  Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
  you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  You may obtain a copy of the License at

      http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.
-->
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V1.2//EN" "document-v12.dtd">
<document> 
  <header> 
    <title>DRAFT: Forrest Project Guidelines</title> 
  </header> 
  <body> 
    <warning>
      This document is under development on the forrest-dev mailing list.
    </warning>
    <p>
     This document provides the guidelines under which the Apache Forrest project operates. It defines the roles and responsibilities, who may vote, how voting works, how conflicts are resolved, etc.
     The Forrest project was established in January 2002 and became a
     top-level project in
     <link href="http://www.apache.org/foundation/records/minutes/2004/">May 2004</link>.
<!-- FIXME: Link directly to the Board minutes when they are available.
-->
    </p>
    <p>
      Forrest is a project of the
      <link href="http://www.apache.org/foundation/">Apache Software
      Foundation (ASF)</link> which holds the copyright for all Apache
      projects. The ASF website explains the operation and background of
      the ASF.
    </p>

    <section id="mission">
      <title>Mission</title>
      <p>
        The generation of aggregated multi-channel documentation,
        maintaining a separation of content and presentation.
      </p>
    </section>

    <section id="roles">
      <title>Roles and Responsibilities</title>
      <section id="users">
        <title>Users</title>
        <p>
          These are the people who download the software and use it for
          their own purposes.
        </p>
      </section>

      <section id="contributers">
        <title>Contributers</title>
        <p>
          These people are users who go the extra step to provide feedback,
          assist other users, contribute discussion, use-cases, minor patches,
          etc.
          They would participate primarily on the "user" mailing list.
        </p>
      </section>

      <section id="developers">
        <title>Developers</title>
        <p>
          These people are contributers who make more substantial contributions.
          They get more involved in discussion, especially discussion about
          design issues, help with solving major issues, provide patches with
          new and improved functionality.
          They would participate on both the "dev" and "user" mailing lists.
        </p>
      </section>

      <section id="committers">
        <title>Committers</title>
        <p>
          When developers remain with the project and demonstrate commitment
          to the project in various ways, then they will be noticed and
          invited to become committers. After a successful vote, they are
          provided with a user account and commit access to the source
          repository, which enables them to be far more productive.
          This is 
          <link href="http://www.apache.org/foundation/how-it-works.html#meritocracy">meritocracy</link>
          - they are given more responsibility and can do more work.
        </p>
        <p>
          The responsibilities of committers include:
          </p>
        <ul>
          <li>Ensuring that they do not add code that has copyright and
           license issues.</li>
          <li>Keeping oversight of the commit log messages.</li>
        </ul>
        <p>
          All Apache committers are required to have a signed Contributor
          License Agreement (CLA) recorded on file with the Apache Software
          Foundation. The
          <link href="http://www.apache.org/dev/committers.html">Committer FAQ</link>
          provides more details about the requirements for committers.
        </p>
      </section>

      <section id="pmc">
        <title>Project Management Committee (PMC)</title>
        <p>
        The PMC is responsible to the Board and the ASF for the management
        and oversight of the Apache Forrest codebase and community.
        Any committer who so chooses can be on the PMC.
        The responsibilities include:
        </p>
        <ul>
          <li>Resolving license disputes regarding products of the project,
            including other supporting software that is re-distributed.</li>
          <li>Deciding what is distributed as products of the project.
            In particular all releases must be approved by the PMC.</li>
          <li>Maintaining the project's shared resources, including the
            codebase repository, mailing lists, websites.</li>
          <li>Speaking on behalf of the project.</li>
          <li>Maintaining these and other guidelines of the project.</li>
        </ul>
        <p>
          The PMC does have a private mailing list on which it can discuss
          certain issues. However this list is rarely used and every effort
          is made to conduct all discussion on the public mailing lists.
        </p>
        <p>
          The chair person of the PMC is appointed by the ASF board.
          The chair is an office holder of the Apache Software Foundation
          (Vice President, Apache Forrest) and has primary responsibility to
          the board for the management of the project, within the scope of
          the Forrest PMC. The chair provides quarterly reports to the board
          about developments within the Forrest project. The PMC may consider
          the position of PMC chair annually, and may recommend a new chair
          to the board. Ultimately, however, it is the board's responsibility
          who it chooses to appoint as the PMC chair.
        </p>
        <fixme author="anybody">
          Add the reasons why committers would want to be on the PMC
          (e.g. legal protection; guide the direction of the project; etc.).
        </fixme>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section id="decisions">
      <title>Decision making</title>
      <section id="voting">
        <title>Voting procedures</title>
        <fixme author="anybody">
          Add content, probably borrow from other projects,
          like Ant and Incubator. Define +1, 0, -1, etc.
          Define situations that require voting (e.g. technical issues,
          new committers, project direction and decisions) and whose votes
          are binding in those situations.
        </fixme>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section id="code">
      <title>Code management</title>
      <p>
      Commit then review.
      </p>
    </section>

  </body>
</document>
