<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V1.1//EN" "document-v11.dtd">
<document> 
  <header> 
    <title>Welcome to Forrest</title> 
  </header> 
  <body> 
    <section>
      <title>Introduction</title>
        <p>Forrest is an XML standards-oriented project documentation framework
         based on Apache Cocoon, providing XSLT stylesheets and schemas, images
         and other resources. Forrest uses these to render the XML source
         content into a website via command-line, robot, or a dynamic web
         application.
        </p>

      <p>Our first target is to create a consistent
        <link href="http://xml.apache.org/">xml.apache.org</link> website, with a
      uniform, lightweight, easy-to-navigate layout and structure. Each project
      will be responsible for maintaining its own documentation and website,
      which are imported, aggregated and published automatically by Forrest.
      The framework is intentionally designed to allow Forrest to also be
      applied in other projects.
      </p>

      <p>The Forrest framework comprises XML document grammars for the different
       types of documents that a project website typically consists of, a
       skinning facility to easily apply a different user interface, local and
       robot-based build systems to draw XML content from a repository and
       publish to local or remote sites, and a
      <link href="http://xml.apache.org/cocoon/">Cocoon</link>-based site
      generation mechanism.</p> 
      <p>The Forrest developers ... forrest-dev&lt;at&gt;xml.apache.org</p> 
    </section> 
    <section>
      <title>Project Status</title>
      <p>The Forrest project is new and needs your help.</p>
      <ul>
      <li>Read our <link href="primer.html">Forrest Primer</link> to
      understand what Forrest is and how you can use and contribute to it.</li>
      <li>Please see the <link href="faq.html">FAQ</link> and join the
      discussion on the forrest-dev&lt;at&gt;xml.apache.org
      <link href="mail-lists.html">mail list</link>.
      </li>
      <li>Follow the <link href="your-project.html">Using Forrest</link>
       document to generate a website for your own project.
      </li>
      <li>There is also a fledgling <link href="dreams.html">Dream List</link>
      to help provide some direction.</li>
      <li>The 
       <link href="http://xml.apache.org/forrest/">Forrest website</link>
       is updated irregularly and manually, while we develop the
       <link href="forrestbot.html">forrestbot</link> facility
       which produces the
       <link href="http://forrestbot.cocoondev.org/">automatically generated</link> site.
       </li>
      </ul> 
    </section> 
  </body>
</document>
