<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V1.1//EN" "document-v11.dtd">
<document>
  <header>
    <title>Communication</title>
    <authors>
      <person name="unknown" email="unknown"/>
    </authors>
  </header>
  <body>
    <p>
      The Project obtains its strength from the communication of its 
      members. In order for members to easily communicate with each other, 
      the Project has a variety of mailing lists. These lists, with the 
      exception of the announcement lists, are not moderated and anybody is 
      more than welcome to join them. However, you must be subscribed to 
      post to a list.
    </p>
      <p>
      To reduce the bandwidth demands on everyone, mail should not contain 
      attachments. It is recommended that you place interesting material 
      (such as patches) either within the body of the message or provide a 
      URL for retrieval.
    </p>
      <p>
      To join the mailing lists, see our <link href="mail.html">Mailing List</link>
      page.
    </p>
      <p>
      The Project's list fall into the following categories:
    </p>
    <section title="Announcement Lists">
      <p>
      Announcement lists are very low traffic designed to communicate 
      important information, such as final releases of a subproject's 
      code, to a wide audience.
    </p>
    </section>
    <section title="User Lists">
      <p>
      User lists are for users of a product to converse about such things 
      as configuration and operating of the products of the Project.
    </p>
    </section>
    <section title="Developer Lists">
      <p>
      Developer lists are for the developers of the project. On these 
      lists suggestions and comments for code changes are discussed and 
      action items are raised and voted on. For the developer community, 
      these lists are the very center of the project where all the 
      "action" is.
    </p>
    </section>
    <section title="Commit Lists">
      <p>
      The commit lists are where all cvs code commit messages are sent. 
      All committers are required to subscribe to this list so that they 
      can stay aware of changes to the repository. 
    </p>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>
