<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V1.1//EN" "document-v11.dtd">
<document><header><title>Project Guidelines</title><authors><person name="unknown" email="unknown"/></authors></header><body><section title="The xml.apache.org Project Guidelines"><p>
      This document defines the guidelines of the <em>xml.apache.org</em> 
      project. It includes definitions of the various categories of 
      membership, who is able to vote, how conflicts are resolved by voting, 
      and the procedures to follow for proposing and making changes to the 
      codebase of the Project.
    </p><note>
      Note that our sister project, jakarta.apache.org, is formulating 
      a number of other project-wide guidelines that the xml community may 
      wish to copy or modify.  In Sept-2001 there are also a number of 
      discussions on the general@xml.apache.org and commons-dev@xml.apache.org 
      mailing lists about other cross-project guidelines that we hope will 
      standardize our projects and make developing and using them easier.
      Stay tuned!
    </note><p>
      This is a living document. Changes can be made by the Project 
      Management Committee. 
    </p><ul><li><link href="roles.html">Roles and Responsibilities</link>
        Defines the recognized roles in the project.</li><li><link href="communication.html">
    Communication</link>
        Defines how users and developers communicate.</li><li><link href="decisions.html">Decision Making</link>
        Defines how action items are proposed and voted on.</li><li><link href="source.html">Source Repositories</link>
        Defines how the Project's source code is organized and developed.</li><li><link href="management.html">Project Management</link>
        Defines the roles and responsibilities of the Project Management
        Committee (PMC).</li><li><link href="mission.html">Our Mission / Charter</link>
        A copy of the Charter document for the xml.apache.org Project.</li></ul></section><section title="Website update guidelines"><warning>This is <strong>not</strong> valid for projects using Forrest for their documentation needs!</warning><p>
      As XML-oriented projects, so our website is also generated from 
      XML files.  While many similar websites may use servlets or a 
      system like Cocoon to generate their websites on-the-fly 
      from XML documents, we currently checkin source .xml files 
      of the documentation and then generate a static set of .html 
      files for most of this website.
    </p><p>
      Briefly: the entire xml.apache.org website is stored in CVS repositories.
      Both the source .xml documents and the generated .html docs are checked in, 
      and the actual website itself is simply a checked-out copy of the repository.
    </p><p>
      While each subproject's individual areas may be managed separately 
      (by that subproject's committers) the top-level of the website 
      should be managed through the xml-site repository.  Thus to change 
      any of the files at the root of http://xml.apache.org you should 
      first check out the xml-site repository from cvs.apache.org
    </p><p>
      (for updating the top-level docs)
      <br/>Checkout the xml-site module (you only actually need a few subdirs; it's quite large)
      <br/>Make updates to the .xml files in the xml-site/sources/website directory
      <br/>Go to the xml-site/sources directory locally and run website.bat
      <br/>Check that the .html structure in your local targets directory is built correctly
      <br/>Checkin both your updated sources/ and targets/ trees as needed
      <br/>Login to xml.apache.org and cd to /www/xml.apache.org
      <br/>Do an update of directories there as needed
    </p></section></body></document>
