<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V1.1//EN" "document-v11.dtd">
<document>
  <header>
    <title>Reference Library</title>
    <authors>
      <person name="unknown" email="unknown"/>
    </authors>
  </header>
  <body>
    <section title="Reference Library">
      <p>
    The <em>xml.apache.org</em> project lives or fails based on its human resources. Users and
    contributors alike help the project with ideas and brainpower. A common
    foundation of knowledge is required to effectively participate in this virtual
    community. The following is a list of documents that we have found helpful for us
    and may be helpful to you:
    </p>
    </section>
    <section title="Technical Resources">
      <p>
      These resources are required reading for anybody contributing source code to the
      project.
    </p>
      <ul>
        <li>
          <jump href="http://java.sun.com/docs/books/jls/index.html">The Java Language Specification</jump>
          <br/>
        Written by the creators of the Java Programming Language, this online book is
                    considered by many to be the bible for programming in Java. A must read.
      </li>
        <li>
          <jump href="http://java.sun.com/products/jdk/javadoc/index.html">Javadoc</jump>
          <br/>
        Javadoc is the automatic software documentation generator used by Java since it
                    was first released. All Java code written for this project must be documented using
                    Javadoc conventions. 
      </li>
        <li>
          <jump href="http://www.cvshome.org/docs/blandy.html">Introduction to CVS</jump>
          <br/>
        Written by Jim Blandy, this brief introduction gives a first look into CVS. If you
                    have never used CVS before, you'll want to start here. 
      </li>
        <li>
          <jump href="http://www.cvshome.org/docs/cederqvist.html">Version Management with CVS</jump>
          <br/>
        Written by Per Cederqvist at al, this is the main manual for CVS. It provides details
                    on all documented CVS features. 
      </li>
      </ul>
    </section>
    <section title="Source Code Philosophy Resources">
      <p> 
        The following are a set of articles written about the recent source code movements
        that help illustrate some of the attributes of a collaborative project such as this. You
        may not agree with all of the points of these articles, but an understanding of them
        will help in communicating with everyone on the project.
    </p>
      <ul>
        <li>
          <jump href="http://www.tuxedo.org/%7Eesr/writings/cathedral-bazaar/index.html">The Cathedral and the Bazaar</jump>
          <br/>
        Written by Eric S. Raymond, this is a must read for anyone willing to join or
                    support a volunteer project.
      </li>
        <li>
          <jump href="http://www.tuxedo.org/%7Eesr/writings/homesteading/index.html">Homesteading the Noosphere</jump>
          <br/>
        Written by Eric S. Raymond, this is a sequel to "The Cathedral and the Bazaar". It
                    details the property and ownership customs of the open-source culture. This
                    analysis has larg implications for anyone interested in organizing large-scale
                    intellectual collaborations such as this project. 
      </li>
      </ul>
    </section>
    <section title="XML Resources">
      <p>A wide variety of XML-oriented resources are out on the net today.
      Just a few that we have found useful include:
      </p>
      <ul>
        <li>
          <jump href="http://xml.org/">xml.org</jump>
          <br/>
          An industry-sponsored portal with links, news, and a wide variety of resources
        </li>
        <li>
          <jump href="http://xmlhack.com/">xmlhack </jump>
          <br/>
          Find all the latest XML-related news stories here
        </li>
        <li>
          <jump href="http://www.oasis-open.org/cover/">The XML Cover pages</jump>
          <br/>
          Robin Cover's long-standing overview of all things XML
        </li>
        <li>
          <jump href="http://www.xmlsoftware.com/">XMLSOFTWARE</jump>
          <br/>
          A listing of various XML-related tools with brief reviews
        </li>
      </ul>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>
