<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V1.1//EN" "document-v11.dtd">
<document>
  <header>
    <title>Project Management</title>
    <authors>
      <person name="unknown" email="unknown"/>
    </authors>
  </header>
  <body>
    <p>
      The Project Management Committee (PMC) was formed by the Apache Board 
      in September 1999. This Committee consists of X founding members, one 
      of whom is the founding Chairman. The term of the Chairman is one 
      year. There is no term limit for members. The list of current members 
      can be found in our <link href="whoweare.html">Project Credits</link>.
    </p>
    <section title="Roles">
      <p>
        The PMC is responsible for the strategic direction and success of 
        the <em>xml.apache.org</em> Project. This governing body is expected 
        to ensure the project's welfare and guide its overall direction. The 
        PMC may not necessarily participate in the day-to-day coding but is 
        involved in the overall development plans, the alleviation of any 
        bottlenecks, the resolution of conflicts, and the overall technical 
        success of the project.
      </p>
      <p>
        The PMC is answerable to the Apache Board with its Chairman serving 
        as primary liaison.
      </p>
    </section>
    <section title="Meetings">
      <p>
        The PMC meets monthly with a majority of its members to discuss 
        issues, determine strategic direction, and forward progress. These 
        meetings may take place online, via teleconference, or via other 
        means deemed effective by the PMC. The PMC has an annual meeting at 
        which time a new Chairman is elected. The old Chairman maintains 
        membership status.
      </p>
    </section>
    <section title="Membership">
      <p>
        PMC members may resign at any time. The Chairman may resign as 
        Chairman at any time without resigning membership to the PMC. The 
        Chairman or any member may be removed from the PMC by a 3/4 vote of 
        the PMC.
      </p>
    </section>
    <p>
      New members may be elected to the PMC. In order to be elected, a 
      person must have served as a Committer and be nominated by a PMC 
      Member. Once nominated, all of the PMC will vote and those receiving a 
      3/4 positive vote will become a member.
    </p>
  </body>
</document>
