<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V1.1//EN" "document-v11.dtd">
<document>
  <header>
    <title>Roles and Responsibilities</title>
    <authors>
      <person name="unknown" email="unknown"/>
    </authors>
  </header>
  <body>
    <section title="Roles and Responsibilities">
      <p>
      The roles and responsibilities that people can assume in the project 
      are based on merit. Everybody can help no matter what their role. 
      Those who have been long term or valuable contributors to the project 
      obtain the right to vote and commit directly to the source repository.
    </p>
    </section>
    <section title="Users">
      <p>
      Users are the people who use the products of the Project. People in 
      this role aren't contributing code, but they are using the products, 
      reporting bugs, making feature requests, and such. This is by far 
      the most important category of people as, without users, there is no 
      reason for the Project.
    </p>
      <p>
      When a user starts to contribute code or documentation patches, they
      become a developer.
    </p>
    </section>
    <section title="Developers">
      <p>
      Developers are the people who write code or documentation patches or 
      contribute positively to the project in other ways. A developer's 
      contribution is always recognized. In source code, all developers 
      who contribute to a source file may add their name to the list of 
      authors for that file.
    </p>
    </section>
    <section title="Committers">
      <p>
      Developers who give frequent and valuable contributions to a 
      subproject of the Project can have their status promoted to that of 
      a "Committer" for that subproject. A Committer has write access to 
      the source code repository and gains voting rights allowing them to 
      affect the future of the subproject.
    </p>
      <p>
      In order for a Developer to become a Committer, another Committer 
      can nominate that Developer or the Developer can ask for it. Once a 
      Developer is nominated, all of the Committers for a subproject will 
      vote. If there are at least 3 positive votes and no negative votes, 
      the Developer is converted into a Committer and given write access 
      to the source code repository for that subproject.
    </p>
      <p>
      At times, Committers may go inactive for a variety of reasons. A 
      Committer that has been inactive for 6 months or more may lose his 
      or her status as a Committer.
    </p>
      <p>
      A list of our current Committers can be found in our
      <link href="whoweare.html">Project Credits</link>.
    </p>
    </section>
    <section title="Project Management Committee (PMC)">
      <p>
      Committers who frequently participate with valuable contributions 
      may have their status promoted to that of a "Project Management 
      Committee Member". This committee is the official managing body of 
      the xml.apache.org Project and is responsible for setting overall 
      project direction. In order to become a Member, someone on the PMC 
      must nominate the Committer. The individual may then be approved 
      with a 3/4 majority of the PMC.
    </p>
      <p>
      To view the Project Management Committee bylaws, 
      <link href="management.html">click here</link>.
    </p>
      <p>
      A list of our current PMC Members can be found in our 
      <link href="whoweare.html">Project Credits</link>.
    </p>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>
