<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more
  contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file distributed with
  this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.
  The ASF licenses this file to You under the Apache License, Version 2.0
  (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with
  the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

      http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.
-->
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN" "http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">
<document>
  <header>
    <title>Forrest Bundles</title>
  </header>
  <body>
    <section id="overview">
      <title>Anatomy of a Forrest bundle</title>
      <p>
        A forrest-osgi plugin is nothing more than a bundle, and a
        bundle is simply a JAR file with OSGi metadata added to the
        manifest. Forrest bundles are assembled from JAR files using
        the bnd Ant task. See the <a href="ext:bnd">bnd tool</a> for
        more information. The bndwrap task is also available as an
        option, but bnd seems to be less lenient and leads to fast
        discovery of build problems.
      </p>
      <p>
        The bnd task is given the name of a file,
        <code>log4j.bnd</code> for example, which controls how bnd
        operates. There are also options given directly as attributes
        to the bnd task within the Ant file.
      </p>
      <p>
        The assembled bundles are gathered together in the
        <code>bundle</code> directory, from which the launcher
        installs them in the framework and starts them.
      </p>
      <p>
        Some dependencies of forrest-osgi come in the form of bundles,
        ready for OSGi. These are found in <code>lib/bundle</code>,
        which are copied to <code>bundle</code> as part of the build
        process.
      </p>
    </section>
    <section id="implementation">
      <title>Implementation choices</title>
      <p>
        There are several implementation choices available for an
        OSGi-driven Forrest given the way the framework handles
        bundles. Forrest plugins can be discovered by the use of
        custom manifest headers; they can announce their presence by
        publishing a service; they can bind to a published service and
        register their existence through that service. There are many
        choices available.
      </p>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>
