<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more
  contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file distributed with
  this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.
  The ASF licenses this file to You under the Apache License, Version 2.0
  (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with
  the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

      http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.
-->
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN" "http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">
<document>
  <header>
    <title>Content Integration - Aggregating multiple content</title>
  </header>
  <body>
    <section id="status">
      <title>Site Objectives</title>
      <p>The initial main aims of this example site is to be a proving ground and showcase of sorts for just a few of what Apache Forrest can do to make things easier.
      </p>
      <p>Some of the things this site can (or will) do are :</p>
      <ul>
              <li>Convert local and remote TEI based documents for display in this site as <acronym title="Hypertext Markup Language">HTML</acronym></li>
              <li>Make the same content available for downloading in OpenOffice.org 2.3+ Writer program in the OpenDocument based ODT format.</li>
              <li>Pull in other sources and formats of information such as Wikipedia, Google Wiki, Media Wiki and using Simal and OSSWatch for some example remote content also.</li>
              <li>A new References Section has been added to this site which summarises all links on a page (and only appears if there are links to process, unlike this page).</li>
      </ul>
      <p>The current ODT output template is based on a donated template by OSSWatch. At some stage in the future there should be alternative templates offered.</p>
      <p>The rest of this site is dedicated to providing working examples and documenting how these are made to work.</p>
      <warning>This example site is in need of improvment, it also suffers from a few Issues - currently the site will
              work fine under 'forrest run' but will not build as a static site due to our use of remote documents.</warning>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>
