<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more
  contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file distributed with
  this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.
  The ASF licenses this file to You under the Apache License, Version 2.0
  (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with
  the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

      http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.
-->
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN" "http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">
<document>
  <header>
    <title>Welcome to the org.apache.forrest.plugin.input.ecs Plugin</title>
  </header>
  <body>
    <section id="overview">
      <title>Apache Forrest - org.apache.forrest.plugin.input.ecs Plugin</title>
      <p>Takes responses from Amaqzons Web Services (ECS) and renders them within a Forrest site.</p>
    </section>

    <section id="usage">
      <title>Usage</title>
      <p>Unfortunately Amazon does not serve content with a doctype identifier. This
      makes it impossible for Forrest to work out which transformations need to be 
      applied. Consequently, we need to use a naming convention to inform Forrest
      when a file is a an Amazon file. You can use the Locationmap to hide this
      naming structure from your users. However, in this document and the enclosed
      samples we will using the required naming convention directly so that you can
      see how it works.</p>

      <p>All requests to be processed by this plugin must have an *.ecs.* filename.
      The first wildcard is the requested file, the second is the requested 
      format. The source files themselve must be named *.ecs.amazon.xml for the
      Amazon response file. In addition you can provide an *.ecs.local.xml that defines
      additional local information, such as your own editoriak review.</p>

      <p>You can retrieve the original ECS response by requesting *.ecs.source.xml.</p>
    </section>
    
    <section>
      <title>Static or Live Data?</title>
      <p>Using the locationmap it is possible to retrieve live data from Amazon
      when running Forrest in dynamic mode. However, please be aware of Amazons
      rules regarding caching of data.</p>
    </section>
    
    <section>
      <title>Layout</title>
      
      <note>Currently this plugin uses the "old fashioned" skinning system
      of Forrest 0.7 and earlier. However, it will soon be modified to use
      the brand spanking new "forrest:views" system in 0.8. This will provide 
      much more control over the layout and use of data within an Amazon page.
      In the meantime you have full control over the layout of an ECS page using
      CSS, as described below.</note>
      
      <p>All elements are enclosed within <code>&lt;div&gt;</code> elements
      to enable the site designer to control the laout of their page using CSS.
      This table below indicates the names of these section for various parts
      of the webpage.</p>
      
      <table>
        <tr>
          <th>Page Element</th>
          <th>div @id</th>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>Item Attributes</td>
          <td>ecs_itemAttributes</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>Batteries Information</td>
          <td>ecs_batteries</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>Manufacturer Information</td>
          <td>ecs_manufacturer</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>Pricing Information</td>
          <td>ecs_price</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>More details link</td>
          <td>ecs_moreDetails</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>Small Image</td>
          <td>ecs_smallImage</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>Medium Image</td>
          <td>ecs_mediumImage</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>Large Image</td>
          <td>ecs_largeImage</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>Editorial Reviews</td>
          <td>ecs_editorialReviews</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>Customer Reviews</td>
          <td>ecs_customerReviews</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>Summary of Customer Reviews</td>
          <td>ecs_customerReviewsSummary</td>
        </tr>
      </table>
      
      <p>There are a couple of exceptions to this rule. Items such as customer reviews
      and editorial reviews sometimes recur for multiple values. In this case we cannot
      use the id attribute, so we assing a class to the div instead. The table below
      describes the class name, this name will have the element number at the
      end (in place of the asterisk in the table).</p>
      
      
      <table>
        <tr>
          <th>Page Element</th>
          <th>div @class</th>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>Editorial Review</td>
          <td>ecs_editorailReview_*</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>Customer Review</td>
          <td>ecs_customerReview_*</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>Additional Small Images</td>
          <td>ecs_smallImage_*</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>Additional Medium Images</td>
          <td>ecs_mediumImage_*</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>Additional Large Images</td>
          <td>ecs_largeImage_*</td>
        </tr>
      </table>
      
      <p>You can find examples of how to use this CSS to control the display of
      your product page in the plugins skinconf.xml file.</p>
    </section>
          

    <section>
      <title>Status</title>
      <p>Support of item lookups is fairly complete, but support of 
      the search results is minimal.</p>
    </section>

    <section id="samples">
      <title>Samples</title>
      <p>This section includes links to a number of samples using this plugin. The
      plugin is intended to be self documenting through these samples. If you 
      require further help please ask on the user mailing list.</p>

      <ul>
        <li>
          <a href="sample/itemLookup1.ecs.html">An Item Lookup</a>
        </li>
        <li>
          <a href="sample/itemSearch1.ecs.html">An Item Search</a>
        </li>
      </ul>

      <note>The more samples included here the easier it is for users to
      understand this plugin. If you can provide additional samples please
      do so.</note>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>
