<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more
  license agreements.  See the NOTICE file distributed with
  this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.
  The ASF licenses this file to You under the Apache License, Version 2.0
  (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with
  the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

      http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.
-->
<useCases>
  <title>Uses Cases for org.apache.forrest.plugin.input.projectInfo</title>

  <useCase>
    <title>Write Use Case Documentation</title>
    <description>
      <p>Write semi-structured use case documents so that they can be reused in a variety of ways.
      This use case describews a process for writing such documents. This document is derived from
      such a <a href="useCases.source.xml">source document</a>.</p>

      <section>
        <title>Justification</title>

        <p>A use case describes a unit of work. It is typically used in the design
        stages of a software project. It is very useful for describing what an applicaiton must
        do and what patchs through the system can be taken.</p>

        <p>By bringing this information together in a semi-structured document we can use it in many
        different ways. For example:</p>

        <ul>
          <li>Requirements Documentation</li>
          <li>Developer Documentation</li>
          <li>User Documentaiton</li>
          <li>Functionality Matrices</li>
          <li>Task Lists</li>
        </ul>
      </section>
      
    </description>

    <steps>
      <step>
        <title>Create/open a Use Case file</title>
        <description>In your favourite XML editor either create a new file
        or open an existing use case file. The default location of these files
        within a Forrest content object is <code>/content/documentation/xdocs/useCases.xml</code>
        </description>
        <result>You have either a blank use case document or an existing one ready for editing.</result>

        <fixme priority="High">Create a DTD for use case descriptions.</fixme>
      </step>

      <step>
        <title>Create a new use case</title>
        <description>
          <p>A use case is enclosed within a <code>useCase</code> element.
          Each use case should be given a brief <code>title</code> to describe it.</p>

        </description>

        <result>You have the container for your new use case.</result>
        
        <fixme priority="High">Allow use cases to be split over several files.</fixme>
      </step>

        <step>
          <title>Describe the overall objective of the use case</title>
          <description>
            <p>Each use case should be described in terms of:</p>
            <ul>
              <li>The objective</li>
              <li>The expected results</li>
              <li>The justification</li>
            </ul>
            <p>This information should be placed in the <code>description</code> element
          of your use case. This node allows any XDoc markup and therefore you are
          reasonably free to use whatever formatting or images are needed to convey the
          important details most efficiently.</p>
          </description>

          <result>You have a use case that is described sufficiently well for an average user of the end system
        to understand its purpose.</result>
        </step>

        <step>
          <title>Define each step in the Use Case</title>
          <description>
            <p>Each use case will be subdivided into one or more steps that must be carried out
          in order to complete the task. Each of these steps is defined within a <code>step</code>
          element which are chilren of a <code>steps</code> element.</p>
          </description>
        </step>

        <step>
          <title>Descripbe the step</title>
          <description>
            <p>Each step has a title and a description. The description should provide enough information
            for a user to complete the task and for a developer to implement support for the user in that
            task.</p>

            <p>In addition each step can be described as required or optional. By default a step is assumed
            be required. To set it to optional add a <code>required="false"</code> attribute to the
            <code>step</code> element.</p>
          </description>

          <result>A user will be able to follow instructions on how to carry out the step.</result>
        </step>

        <step>
          <title>Describe the expected results</title>
          <description>
            <p>Provide, within a <code>result</code> a brief description of the expected results from
            this step. This should summarise what state the application will be in once this use case
            has been performed.</p>
          </description>
          <result>You will have provided enough information to allow developers to test the functionality and
          users to identify when a step has been succesfully completed.</result>
        </step>

        <step required="false">
          <title>Add "fixme" notes</title>
          <description>
            <p>A fixme note is enclosed within a <code>fixme</code> element. It describes something that
            remains to be done within this step. Each fixme has a priority attribute which can take one of
            of the followin values:</p>

            <ul>
              <li>Enhancement - a nice to have ehancment that may or may not be implemented.</li>
              <li>Low - this is considered an important addition to the use case, but everything works without it.</li>
              <li>High - this is an important addition. Everything works without it, but having this implmeneted would
              improve the application considerably.</li>
              <li>Major - this is nor preventing work that utilises the use case, but it is considered a requirement
              for the next release since it adds key functionlaity.</li>
              <li>Blocker - this is preventing the correct operation of this use case and must be implmeneted ASAP</li>
            </ul>

            <p>Although this step is optional, it is good practice to allways add a 
            <code>&lt;fixme priority="blocker"&gt;Not yet implemented&lt;/fixme&gt;</code>
            element to all new steps. This is becuase these nodes will be used to build a 
            functionality matrix later on.</p>
          </description>

          <result>Users will be able to understand to what degree a step is implemented and developers will be able to 
          see what remains to be done.</result>
          
          <fixme priority="enhancement">All fixmes to link to an issue tracker entry</fixme>
        </step>

        <step required="false">
          <title>Add alternatives</title>
          <description>
            <p>Sometimes there will be alternative paths through each step. These can be described in an
            <code>alternatives</code> element that allows free-form XDoc content. However, please be
            careful, if an alternative is more than a simple variation you may want to consider a 
            whole new use case for the alternative.</p>
          </description>

          <result>Minor variations in the path through a use case will be documented for your users.</result>
        </step>
        
        <step required="false">
          <title>Write Implementation Notes</title>
          <description>
            <p>Developer implementation notes for each of the steps should be added either when writing the
            initial use case or later during the development phases of the use case. These notes are for technical readers
            and are intended to help those who come after the initial author to get a starting point when inspecting how
            a feature is implemented. It is not intended that these notes will contain full implementation details, only an
            overview should be provided.</p>
          </description>
          
          <result>A technical reader will be able to gain a baisc understanding of how each step is implemented in the 
          application.</result>
        </step>          
    </steps>
  </useCase>

  <useCase status="In Progress" owner="open">
    <title>Generate Use Case Documentation for Developers</title>

    <description>
      <p>Generate a complete list of all use cases for a project in a format useful to 
      developers of the application. This list is to include:</p>

      <ul>
        <li>a description of the use case</li>
        <li>a summary of each of the steps involved</li>
        <li>full details of each of the steps</li>
        <li>a description of the expected outcome of each step</li>
        <li>details of common alternatives in each step</li>
        <li>implementation notes for each step</li> 
      </ul>

      <section>
        <title>Justification</title>
        <p>A use case describes a unit of work. It is typically used in the design
        stages of a software project, however, they can often be useful in creating
        user documentaiton. Especially when they describe user interface functionality.</p>

        <warning>Unfortunately this use case document does not currently cover all functions
        of the plugin since this functionlaity was added after many other features. Whilst you
        are exploring this feature, why not add a use case to the plugin and submit a patch
        so that those coming after you can enjoy more complete documentation.</warning>
      </section>
    </description>

    <steps>
      <step>
        <title>Make HTTP request</title>
        <description>
          <p>
            Request
            http://localhost:8888/docs/developer/useCases.xml
          </p>
        </description>
        <result>
          <p>
            An XDoc is created that describes the use cases
          </p>
        </result>

        <fixme priority="High">Make the summary optional - already added 
        $includeImplementationNotes parameter to stylesheet. Need to pass value form sitemap.</fixme>
        
        <alternatives>
          <p>Depending on what plugins are available within your running instance of Forrest you will
          be able to request different output formats as per the usual Forrest usage. For example requesting
          a http://localhost:8888/docs/developer/useCases.html will generate the HTML document, whilst
          http://localhost:8888/docs/developer/useCases.pdf will generate the PDF document (as long
          as you have the relevant plugins installed).</p>
        </alternatives>

        <implementation>
          <description>
            <p>The source document for use cases is, by default, called <code>useCases.xml</code> and is
            located in the root of the projects xdocs directory.</p>

            <p>The URL space <code>docs/**/useCases.xml</code> is reserved for the projectInfo plugin. A request to
            /docs/developer/useCases.xml results in the useCases.xml file being translated into an XDoc as per
            the usual forrest processing. See the input.xmap file fo this plugin,</p>
          </description>
        </implementation>
      </step>
    </steps>
  </useCase>
  
  <useCase status="In Progress" owner="open">
    <title>Generate Use Case Documentation for Users</title>

    <description>
      <p>Generate a complete list of all use cases for a project. This list is to include:</p>

      <ul>
        <li>a description of the use case</li>
        <li>a summary of each of the steps involved</li>
        <li>full details of each of the steps</li>
        <li>a description of the expected outcome of each step</li>
        <li>details of common alternatives in each step</li>
      </ul>

      <section>
        <title>Justification</title>
        <p>A use case describes a unit of work. It is typically used in the design
        stages of a software project, however, they can often be useful in creating
        user documentaiton. Especially when they describe user interface functionality.</p>

        <warning>Unfortunately the use case document does not currently cover all functions
        of the plugin since this functionlaity was added after many other features. Whilst you
        are exploring this feature, why not add a use case to the plugin and submit a patch
        so that those coming after you can enjoy more complete documentation.</warning>
      </section>
    </description>

    <steps>
      <step>
        <title>Make HTTP request</title>
        <description>
          <p>
            Request
            http://localhost:8888/docs/user/useCases.xml
          </p>
        </description>
        <result>
          <p>
            An XDoc is created that describes the use cases
          </p>
        </result>

        <fixme priority="High">Enable the retrieval of a specific use case rather than all at once.</fixme>
        <fixme priority="Low">Make the summary optional - there is a switch in the XSL for this, just need to pass a property
        from the XMAP</fixme>
        
        <alternatives>
          <p>Depending on what plugins are available within your running instance of Forrest you will
          be able to request different output formats as per the usual Forrest usage. For example requesting
          a http://localhost:8888/docs/user/useCases.html will generate the HTML document, whilst
          http://localhost:8888/docs/user/useCases.pdf will generate the PDF document (as long
          as you have the relevant plugins installed).</p>
        </alternatives>

        <implementation>
          <description>
            <p>The source document for use cases is, by default, called <code>useCases.xml</code> and is
            located in the root of the projects xdocs directory.</p>

            <p>The URL space <code>docs/**/useCases.xml</code> is reserved for the projectInfo plugin. A request to
            /docs/user/useCases.xml results in the useCases.xml file being translated into an XDoc as per
            the usual forrest processing, see input.xmap for more details.</p>
          </description>
        </implementation>
      </step>
    </steps>
  </useCase>
  
  <useCase status="In Progress">
    <title>Generate a Functionality Matrix</title>
    <description>
      <p>If a use case document is correcly marked up with <code>fixme</code> elements it is possible
      to create a functionality matrix for each use case. This will show how complete the implementation
      of a use case is.</p>
      
      <p>A table can be created which shows each of the steps in a use case, each step can be given a
      count for the bumber of fixme items outstanding on each of the steps. Furthermore, since each
      <code>fixme</code> is given a priority we can clearly indicate which use cases are operational an 
      hich are not.</p>
    </description>
    
    <steps>
      <step>
        <title>Make HTTP request</title>
        <description>
          <p>
            Request
            http://localhost:8888/docs/developer/featureMatrix/useCases.xml
          </p>
        </description>
        <result>
          <p>
            An XDoc is created that lists the steps in each use case and identifies the status
            of each use case.
          </p>
        </result>

        <fixme priority="Blocker">Not Implemented Yet - although the user and dev use case documents
        do show the status of each step in the details table and implementation notes.</fixme>
        
        <alternatives>
          <p>Depending on what plugins are available within your running instance of Forrest you will
          be able to request different output formats as per the usual Forrest usage. For example requesting
          a http://localhost:8888/docs/developer/featureMatrix/useCases.html will generate the HTML document, whilst
          http://localhost:8888/docs/developer/featureMatrix/useCases.pdf will generate the PDF document (as long
          as you have the relevant plugins installed).</p>
        </alternatives>

        <implementation>
          <description>
            <p>The source document for use cases is, by default, called <code>useCases.xml</code> and is
            located in the root of the projects xdocs directory.</p>

            <p>The URL space <code>docs/**/useCases.xml</code> is reserved for the projectInfo plugin. A request to
            /docs/developer/featureMatrix/useCases.xml results in the useCases.xml file being translated into an XDoc as per
            the usual forrest processing. See the input.xmap file fo this plugin,</p>
          </description>
        </implementation>
      </step>
    </steps>
  </useCase>
</useCases>

