<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD SmartSlides Presentation V1.0//EN" "http://forrest.apache.org/relaxng/smartslides-v10.rnc">
<presentation>
    <metadata>
        <title>Single Source Publishing with Apache Forrest</title>
        <abstract>
            <para>Apache Forrest harnesses the power of Apache Cocoon to build a single source publishing framework,
                based on common standards (xml).</para>
            <para> It is easy to use and extend to suit a wide variety of publishing needs.</para>
            <bulletList>
                <item>Learn how to get started with Forrest in few easy steps.</item>
                <item>Take a closer look at the design concepts behind Forrest.</item>
                <item> See that it can be easy to publish a single document to very different target media (Web, print,
                    speech, presentation slides) in a consistent and uniform way.</item>
                <item>Find out about 'smart' slide presentions you can create with Forrest.</item>
                <item>Take a tour of input-plugins for OpenOffice and other common formats learning how to integrate
                    different document- and data sources in a common corporate design.</item>
                <item>Discover Forrest's potential to quickly embed dynamic data from local and remote systems.</item>
            </bulletList>
        </abstract>
        <author>
            <fullName>Ferdinand Soethe</fullName>
            <email>ferdinand@apache.org</email>
        </author>
        <author>
            <fullName>Ross Gardler</fullName>
            <email>rgardler@apache.org</email>
        </author>
        <created>2005-07-20</created>
        <updates>
            <updatedby>Ferdinand Soethe</updatedby>
            <changeDate>2005-10-24</changeDate>
        </updates>
        <presenter>
            <fullName>Ferdinand Soethe</fullName>
            <email>ferdinand@apache.org</email>
        </presenter>
    </metadata>
    <content>
        <chapter title="Introduction">
            <page title="Welcome" showOnlyFor="slides">
                <heading>Welcome </heading>
                <para>Good afternoon and welcome to our presentation<br />"<PresentationTitle />" </para>
                <Presenters />
            </page>
            <page title="SSP in a nutshell">
                <heading>Single Source Publishing?</heading>
                <para>Single Source Publishing ...</para>
                <bulletList>
                    <item>is about creating content for different target media from just a single source (document),</item>
                    <item>has the potential to <bulletList>
                            <item>improve media quality,</item>
                            <item>enhance author's satisfaction and</item>
                            <item>save you time and money.</item>
                        </bulletList>
                    </item>
                </bulletList>
            </page>
            <page title="Goals of this Session">
                <heading>Goals of this Session</heading>
                <para>In this session we&apos;ll</para>
                <bulletList>
                    <item>talk about Apache Forrest, the affordable publishing-solution,</item>
                    <item>show you how simple it is to get started,</item>
                    <item>explain the power in Forrest&apos;s architecture and</item>
                    <item>give you a tour of useful applications.</item>
                </bulletList>
            </page>
            <page title="About Ferdinand">
                <heading>Here for You today ...</heading>
                <para>Ferdinand Soethe</para>
                <para>
                    <image id="ferdinandsphoto" url="images/ferdinand.jpg" alternativeText="Ferdinand's photo" />
                </para>
                <bulletList class="incremental">
                    <item>Systems Analyst, Technical Writer and Consultant</item>
                    <item>Committer and Member of Forrest PMC</item>
                    <item>Currently working on the Smart Presentations PlugIn <todo assignedTo="fso">add url to plugin
                            and raw site</todo>
                    </item>
                </bulletList>
                <para class="clearBoth" />
                <addlInfo title="Who can I ask?">
                    <para>Fell free to contact me privately by email (<xref url="mailto:ferdinand@apache.org"
                            >ferdinand@apache.org</xref>). Post questions about Apache Forrest to one of the Apache
                        Forrest project mailing lists (<xref url="http://forrest.apache.org/mail-lists.html"
                            >http://forrest.apache.org/mail-lists.html</xref>)</para>
                </addlInfo>
            </page>
            <page title="Agenda" class="incremental">
                <bulletList>
                    <item>
                        <para>Presentation (40 minutes)</para>
                        <TOC />
                    </item>
                    <item>Questions &amp; Answers (10 minutes) <talk>
                            <bulletList>
                                <item>Suggest ways to participate</item>
                                <item>How and when to ask questions</item>
                            </bulletList>
                        </talk>
                    </item>
                </bulletList>
            </page>
        </chapter>
        <chapter title="Publishing Facts 2005">
            <page title="The WYSIWYG-Trap">
                <talk>Let&apos;s talk about some facts of publishing today:</talk>
                <bulletList>
                    <item>
                        <para>Hardly any word processing software lives up to the promise</para>
                        <talk>
                            <bulletList>
                                <item>You rarely see what you will get.</item>
                                <item>Tools that deliver to the promise are expensive and require professional type
                                    setting knowledge</item>
                            </bulletList>
                        </talk>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <para>Writing and typesetting often are incompatible skills</para>
                        <talk>
                            <bulletList>
                                <item>Few authors create perfect layouts</item>
                                <item>Content (and budget) often suffers.</item>
                            </bulletList>
                        </talk>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <para>WYSIWYG-Documents translate poorly to other media</para>
                        <talk>Let me show you some examples from exporting a word document.</talk>
                    </item>
                </bulletList>
                <addlInfo title="WYSIWYG: Success or Failure">
                    <para>Wikipedia has the following <xref url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wysiwyg">entry for
                        WYSIWYG</xref>:</para>
                    <bulletList>
                        <item>
                            <para>A description of a user interface that allows the user to view the end result while
                                the document or graphic character is being created.<br /> For example, a user can see on
                                screen how a document will look when printed.</para>
                        </item>
                        <item>Allows the user to concentrate entirely on how the content should appear.</item>
                        <item>Also refers to the ability of modifying the layout of a document without having to type
                            (and remember) names of layout commands.</item>
                        <item>Also used to describe specifically a web-page creation program in which the user creates
                            the web page visually, while the program generates the HTML for it. Often users can also
                            edit this HTML if they so desire.</item>
                    </bulletList>
                    <para>WYSIWYG, is becoming increasingly difficult to realise. This is partly because we often want
                        to use the same content in different environments. To reuse content in a WYSIWYG environment
                        usually means one has to re-edit the layout for each publication. Furthermore, using the same
                        tool for content editing and layout means that the writer of the content must also play the role
                        of layout designer. Two skills that are rarely present in any one individual.</para>
                    <para>Where WYSIWYG is useful is in single use documents that are unlikely to be further processed
                        in any way, perhaps for a quick, informal letter to a friend. However, in the business
                        environment it is unusual to create content that will not need to be further processed.</para>
                    <para>For further discussion about the history of WYSIWYG and a discussion of its strengths and
                        weakness see <xref url="http://www.ideography.co.uk/library/seybold/WYSIWYG.html">What has
                            WYSIWYG done to us? (http://www.ideography.co.uk/library/seybold/WYSIWYG.html)</xref>, first
                        published in 1996. The author observes:</para>
                    <para>
                        <em>how we were seduced by WYSIWYG&apos;s illusion of control and how we lowered our
                            expectations and typographic standards and became deeply confused about who in publishing is
                            supposed to do what.</em>
                    </para>
                    <para>He goes on to conclude:</para>
                    <para>
                        <em>Good typography requires a lot more than good-quality typefaces. It also requires improved
                            composition algorithms within publishing software -- both for paper and for the Web.</em>
                    </para>
                    <para>It is interesting to read this paper today, nearly ten years later. The majority of issues and
                        problems identified in that paper are still of great concern. In fact, with the growth of the
                        Web Publishing and "user level" tools for "easy" "publishing" the issues raised within become
                        even more important.</para>
                </addlInfo>
            </page>
            <page title="Examples of HTML Export problems with Microsoft Word">
                <todo>show document and result side by side</todo>
                <bulletList>
                    <item>
                        <para>
                            <xref url="images/word_export_browser_screenshot1.jpg">Table Of Contents Become
                            Meaningless</xref>
                        </para>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <para>
                            <xref url="images/word_export_browser_screenshot2.jpg">Inexplicable Whitespace
                            Inserted</xref>
                        </para>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <para>
                            <xref url="images/word_export_browser_screenshot3.jpg">Bad Layout of Objects</xref>
                        </para>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <para>
                            <xref url="images/word_export_mixed_content_and_style.jpg">Mixing of Content and Style
                                Information</xref>
                        </para>
                    </item>
                </bulletList>
                <talk>
                    <bulletList>
                        <item>dangers of all the extra info that MSWORD includes in its html-files</item>
                        <item>State: HTML-Export is not Web-publishing</item>
                    </bulletList>
                </talk>
                <addlInfo title="Additional Information">
                    <para>Here are just a few examples from a single Microsoft Word Document exported as an HTML page
                        using the latest editition of MS Word. This document was pulled randomly from the Internet to
                        illustrate the dangers of using a word processor to create content intended for use in any
                        environment other than the originating word processor.</para>
                    <section title="Table Of Contents Become Meaningless">
                        <para>When a word processor creates a tables of contents it usually inserts a special marker
                            into the content itself indicating that the contents should be displayed at the given point.
                            However, this is not always the appropriate location or method for creating a table of
                            contents.</para>
                        <image class="screenshots" url="images/word_export_browser_screenshot1.jpg"
                            alternativeText="Table of Contents Relevant only to                             Print" />
                        <para>The screenshot shows how this chosen document has created a table of contents that refers
                            to the page number that the content appears on. But this is a web page rendering, there are
                            no page numbers. It would be more appropriate to create a table of contents with hyperlinks
                            to the relevant section of the web page. Alternatively, we may choose to place the Table of
                            Contents in the navigation menu of the site. With this HTML export it is impossible to do
                            this without editing the exported file. This is hardly Single Source Publishing.</para>
                    </section>
                    <section title="Inexplicable Whitespace Inserted">
                        <para>In this screenshot we can see that for some strange reason there is a large chunk of
                            whitespace inserted between the table header and the table itself. This whitespace cannot be
                            seen in the original document so clearly, the editor is failing in its goal of WYSIWYG
                            editing.</para>
                        <image class="screenshots" url="images/word_export_browser_screenshot2.jpg"
                            alternativeText="Large  amounts of meningless                             whitespace are
                            inserted" />
                    </section>
                    <section title="Bad Layout of Objects">
                        <para>In this final screenshot we see an example of the word processors failure to translate
                            layout of objects correctly to the screen. Notice how the Date object is not aligned with
                            other meta data elements, in fact, it is hidden behind the image. In addition notice how the
                            text is incorrectly appearing to the right of the image and then wrapping below the image.
                            In the editing environment this text all appears below the image. Again, a complete failure
                            of the editor to provide a WYSIWYG environment.</para>
                        <image url="images/word_export_browser_screenshot3.jpg" alternativeText="Objects overlap One
                            Another" />
                    </section>
                    <section title="Mixing of Content and Style Information">
                        <para>Not content with mixing style and content (which we now know is a bad thing) it also seems
                            "necessary" to create hugely complex and bloated embedded style sheets. This creates long
                            load times and prevents central control over the websites style.</para>
                        <para>To even further complicate things there is often a wild mix of html-formatting (align),
                            element-local styles and style-sheet references. This makes it very hard to predict the
                            outcome or even edit the styles in a consistent way.</para> g </section>
                </addlInfo>
            </page>
            <page title="The Internet Publishing Chore">
                <para>Publishing to the Internet is a requirement for corporate business and non-profits.</para>
                <para>It&apos;s complex and costly to design Web-Sites that</para>
                <bulletList>
                    <item>look great,</item>
                    <item>navigate easily,</item>
                    <item>offer full access with a browser of choice,</item>
                    <item>and satisfy all standards. </item>
                </bulletList>
                <addlInfo title="Web-Site Usability">
                    <para>A good web interface is based more in website usability than graphical rendering.</para>
                    <para>A consistent visual design will provide the necessary orientation cues and navigational
                        controls critically needed by users. A successful implementation of these website usability
                        techniques will guarantee that your users will find the information they are looking for in the
                        most efficient and pleasing manner.</para>
                    <para>Unfortunately, maintaining a consistent look and feel is almost impossible when content
                        editors are given WYSIWYG tools. Where one editor will use headings classes others will use
                        bold.</para>
                </addlInfo>
            </page>
            <page title="The tools dilemma">
                <para>Most Web-Design tools were designed for marketing rather than publishing so they</para>
                <bulletList>
                    <item>tweak html until pages look good,</item>
                    <item>make graphic designers happy</item>
                    <item>fulfill advertising needs.</item>
                </bulletList>
                <para>Unfortunately they usually do <em>not</em></para>
                <bulletList>
                    <item>satisfy our criteria,</item>
                    <item>create good looking print versions</item>
                </bulletList>
                <para>
                    <strong>And easy maintenance is usually low on the list!</strong>
                </para>
            </page>
            <page title="Summary">
                <heading>In Summary</heading>
                <para>As a Result:</para>
                <bulletList>
                    <item>Most documents are prepared for publishing twice.</item>
                    <item>The costs are enormous!</item>
                    <item>The results are poor!</item>
                </bulletList>
            </page>
        </chapter>
        <chapter title="A Look At Alternatives">
            <page title="It's Time for a change!">
                <heading>Time for a change!</heading>
                <para>After 20 years of FYO (<strong>F</strong>ormat-<strong>Y</strong>our-<strong>O</strong>wn)
                    it&apos;s time to look for alternatives based on the requirements of a modern publishing
                    concept:</para>
                <bulletList>
                    <item>Authors know the meaning of their text!</item>
                    <item>Typesetting and Web design are professional tasks!</item>
                    <item>It makes sense to keep them separate!</item>
                </bulletList>
                <para>Think about cost!</para>
                <para>
                    <strong>We need to make professional typesetting and Web design affordable!</strong>
                </para>
            </page>
            <page title="Publishing Requirements">
                <heading>Multimedia Publishing Requirements</heading>
                <para>This leads to three simple requirements:</para>
                <bulletList>
                    <item>Create all media from the same document.</item>
                    <item>Automatically apply formatting-templates.</item>
                    <item>Cut costs of professional typesetting and Web design</item>
                </bulletList>
                <addlInfo title="Aditional Requirements?">
                    <para>It can certainly be argued that there are many more requirements in a publishing environment.
                        However, these are the ones that are not adequately covered by current publishing tools.</para>
                </addlInfo>
            </page>
            <page title="Solution: Single Source Publishing">
                <heading>Consider Single Source Publishing</heading>
                <comment>The OpenOffice skill-document for this demo will have a very obvious semantic markup. Since we
                    started with an office document, I&apos;m coming back to showing an office document as source
                    here. Also because it reduces the number of &apos;new&apos; things and keeps us focussed on
                    semantic markup</comment>
                <para>Single source publishing is about smart document processing:</para>
                <talk>as you can see in this little demo</talk>
                <comment>Don&apos;t talk about next bullets points</comment>
                <bulletList>
                    <item>
                        <para>Semantical markup adds meaning to text:</para>
                        <code>
                            <strong>&lt;author&gt;</strong><br />
                            <strong>&lt;fullName&gt;</strong>Ferdinand Soethe<strong>&lt;/fullName&gt;</strong><br />
                            <strong> &lt;email&gt;</strong>ferdinand@apache.org<strong>&lt;/email&gt;</strong><br />
                            <strong>&lt;/author&gt;</strong></code>
                        <para>The author need not think about looks!</para>
                        <demo>
                            <bulletList>
                                <item>Open a skill document in Firefox</item>
                                <item>Show and explain the semantic markup</item>
                                <item>Rule-based transformations automatically typeset the information.</item>
                            </bulletList>
                        </demo>
                    </item>
                    <item>Applying professionally designed templates results in superior layouts. <demo>
                            <bulletList>
                                <item>Show the rendered page in a browser and briefly comment on the pdf-icon
                                        <talk>Explain that Forrest works with XML documents, xsl transformations</talk>
                                </item>
                                <item> Open an existing Open Office skill document <talk>XML-documents can be also be
                                        edited in a familiar environment like OpenOffice.</talk>
                                </item>
                            </bulletList>
                        </demo>
                    </item>
                </bulletList>
                <addlInfo title="Definition: Single source publishing">
                    <para>From <xref url="http://www.wikipedia.org">Wikipedia</xref>, the free encyclopedia:</para>
                    <para>Single source publishing or single sourcing allows the same content to be used in different
                        documents and in various formats.</para>
                    <para>For example, a software company may have several products with user guides that share a common
                        procedure, like instructions on how to open a file. Rather than maintain duplicate versions of
                        this procedure (one in each manual) the manuals can share the content, perhaps flowing it into
                        the document at the time of publication. Eliminating duplicate content can save translation
                        costs, reduce maintenance costs, improve consistency and reduce errors.</para>
                    <para>Single sourcing also allows the creation of documents in various formats from the same
                        content. For example, a company might use the same content in online help, a printed document
                        and a Web page. With a single source solution, the company only has to update the one source
                        file for the content and regenerate the three outputs.</para>
                    <para>Ideally, a single source solution does not require human intervention to customize the
                        formatting or content for the various outputs. This can be difficult to achieve without the use
                        of some kind of content management system.</para>
                </addlInfo>
            </page>
            <page title="Solution: Single Source Publishing ...">
                <heading>Consider SSP (cont)...</heading>
                <bulletList>
                    <item>Customizing the general layouts to create individual site design shares template cost among
                        many users. <demo>Change location of toc by changing skinconfig</demo>
                        <talk>Explain that Forrest skins use CSS design.</talk>
                    </item>
                    <item>Applying different transformations, information can be served to multiple media. <demo>Show
                            generated pdf</demo></item>
                </bulletList>
                <addlInfo title="Single Source Publishing">
                    <para>To produce multiple documents from a single source it is necessary to be able to apply
                        templates to the documents. These templates describe how the document should look. In order to
                        do this it is necessary for the typesetting system to know what the content represents. For
                        example, it must be able to tell the difference between a title of a book and the author of that
                        book. This is known as <xref url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Markup_language">"markup"</xref>.</para>
                    <para>Since an author will understand the semantics of the content they write it is possible for the
                        author to apply a "semantic markup" to the content at the point of authoring. The author need
                        not concern themselves with how this will be presented in the final published version. This
                        enables the author to adopt editing tools that suit their needs as a content editor, they need
                        not encumber themselves with graphical environments designed for typesetting.</para>
                    <para>Just as the content author is freed from the limitations of a typesetting editor, the
                        professional typesetter need no longer concern themselves with content and content editing
                        tools. They need only address the typesetting of content that is correctly "marked up" with its
                        semantic meaning.</para>
                    <para>Finally, since the content and the layout is completely separate it is possible to apply
                        different typesetting templates to the same content. This allows the content to be published in
                        multiple formats and layouts. Each of these templates will create a version of the content that
                        is "marked up" with presentational information appropriate for the desired usage of the
                    content.</para>
                </addlInfo>
            </page>
        </chapter>
        <chapter title="Facts about Forrest">
            <page title="Forrest Processing explained">
                <heading>Behind the Scenes</heading>
                <comment>show and explain a figure of the document processing in functional steps: input-equalization of
                    foreign formats-gerating html and pdf</comment>
                <image url="images/Forrestprocessing.gif" alternativeText="Forrest Processing" />
                <addlInfo title="Apache Forrest">
                    <para>Apache Forrest is a publishing framework that transforms input from various sources into a
                        unified presentation in one or more output formats. The modular and extensible plugin
                        architecture is based on Apache Cocoon and relevant standards, which separates presentation from
                        content. Forrest can generate static documents, or be used as a dynamic server, or be deployed
                        by its automated facility.</para>
                    <para>For more details see the <xref url="http://wforrest.apache.org">Apache Forrest website
                            (http://wforrest.apache.org)</xref>.</para>
                </addlInfo>
            </page>
            <page title="SSP and Forrest">
                <heading>SSP and Forrest</heading>
                <talk>Summarize the difference between OO taking care of the layout and now the transformation doing it </talk>
                <para>The general concept of Single Source Publishing is not new.</para>
                <talk>
                    <bulletList>
                        <item>SGML was the start of semantic markup languages in the 1970ies</item>
                        <item> XML-Technologies as an enabeling technology is more than 10 years old.</item>
                    </bulletList>
                </talk>
                <para>What&apos;s new is Forrest as a free-to-use framework for Single Source Publishing</para>
                <bulletList>
                    <item>With a focus on practical application,</item>
                    <item>quick and easy to get started and</item>
                    <item>extensible when you need it.</item>
                </bulletList>
                <addlInfo title="Apache Forrest: A Single Source Publishing                     Framework">
                    <para>Forrest is far from a quick and dirty solution. Forrest is built on the world&apos;s
                        leading XML application framework, Apache Cocoon, which provides advanced users with extremely
                        powerful publishing capabilities.</para>
                    <bulletList>
                        <item>Multiple task-specific source XML formats are provided (e.g. How-To, FAQ, change logs and
                            todo lists supported natively), together with a range of non-XML formats including Apache
                            xdocs xml format, plain html documents, some Wiki formats, a subset of DocBook,
                            OpenOffice.org and MS Office.</item>
                        <item>Multiple output formats supported, for example HTML and PDF (using Apache FOP).</item>
                        <item>Native Scalable Vector Graphics rendering. Simply drop the SVG in the appropriate
                            directory and it will be rendered as PNG.</item>
                        <item>Transparent inclusion and aggregation of external content, like RSS news feeds.</item>
                        <item>Full extensibility is possible, for example, databases queries, charting, web services
                            integration.</item>
                        <item>Based on Java and XML standards, Forrest is platform-independent, making for a
                            documentation system that is just as portable as the XML data that it processes.</item>
                    </bulletList>
                </addlInfo>
            </page>
            <page title="How to get started">
                <talk>In our next demo we will show you how easy it is to create and publish a new document with Forrest</talk>
                <bulletList>
                    <item>
                        <para>Install Forrest</para>
                        <talk>
                            <bulletList>
                                <item>Installing Forrest is as simple as unpacking the zip-file.</item>
                                <item> Forrest runs on any system that supports Sun Java </item>
                            </bulletList>
                        </talk>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <para>Create a new project with Forrest</para>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <para>Start Forrest as a server</para>
                        <demo>Forrest run the server and browse it.</demo>
                        <talk>Explain the difference of running or compiling</talk>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <para>Write a document and add it as a new page</para>
                        <demo>Take a skill document from resume-dir and drag and drop it into the business site. Explain
                            that we savaing time.</demo>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <para>Show the results in the browser.</para>
                    </item>
                </bulletList>
                <talk>OK, that looked really simple. No wonder we have so many novice users considering Forrest for
                    their publishing. But how about multiuser and online enviroments?</talk>
                <demo>Open a daisy document in a pre-existing project and edit it. Show the changes showing in Browser</demo>
                <addlInfo title="Getting Help to Get Started">
                    <para>See the <xref url="http://wforrest.apache.org">Apache Forrest website
                            (http://wforrest.apache.org)</xref> and users mailing list for more details.</para>
                </addlInfo>
            </page>
        </chapter>
        <chapter title="Forrest Publishing Features">
            <page title="Forrest Publishing Features">
                <para>Forrest is full of powerful features right from the start!</para>
                <para>Out of the box you get</para>
                <chapterTOC />
            </page>
            <page title="Automatic generation of Web and Print Media" listIn="chapterTOC">
                <demo>Compiles daisy example while fso does this slide</demo>
                <para>Forrest will automatically generate output in html- (Web) and pdf-Format (Print) from a single
                    source.</para>
                <para>In contrast to most legacy systems, this output</para>
                <bulletList>
                    <item> looks good, </item>
                    <item> prints well, </item>
                    <item>conforms to all important web-standards,</item>
                    <item>
                        <para>and is fully functional online and offline.</para>
                    </item>
                </bulletList>
                <demo>
                    <bulletList>
                        <item>Open a long document in HTML (these slides) and the pdf along with it. Point out that
                            is&apos;s truely functional pdf (with clickable toc) and will also serve as high quality
                            print version if needed(has toc with page numbers , headers, footers etc.)</item>
                        <item>Show aggregated HTML, different views and aggregated All-site-PDF</item>
                    </bulletList>
                </demo>
                <addlInfo title="A Running Start">
                    <para>Apache Forrest provides a running start in Single Source Publishing. It will generate a range
                        of output formats together with any necessary usability content such as navigation menus in web
                        sites, tables of contents in printed materials. It comes preconfigured with templates for HTML
                        and Print output formats and will even manage the publication of your content to your chosen
                        server.</para>
                </addlInfo>
            </page>
            <page title="Site-Navigation" listIn="chapterTOC">
                <para>Tabs and menues for site-navigation are automatically generated from simple structure for a site
                    that</para>
                <demo>Show and explain navigation features.</demo>
                <bulletList>
                    <item>looks good,</item>
                    <item>is easy to understand,</item>
                    <item>and is tested and works properly with most clients.</item>
                </bulletList>
            </page>
            <page title="Support for Accessibility Requirements" listIn="chapterTOC">
                <para>Forrest already implements many requirements of accessibility guidlines that</para>
                <bulletList>
                    <item> require you to present information in a way that makes access independend of capabilities and
                        features or your client device, </item>
                    <item>are or are about to become law in many parts of the world,</item>
                    <item>and a must for many corporate business sites.</item>
                </bulletList>
                <talk>
                    <para>Accessibilty is not just about access for the handicapped!</para>
                </talk>
                <talk>important for all kinds of non discriminating access by legacy applications, search engines, pdas
                    etc.</talk>
            </page>
            <page title="Flexible staging options" listIn="chapterTOC">
                <para>Forrest output can be presented in a variety of ways</para>
                <bulletList>
                    <item>Static HTML for cheap hosting and easy distribution on CD or DVD,</item>
                    <item>Application Server if you need powerful interactive features,</item>
                    <item>
                        <para>Build and deploy robot for time delayed updates of static sites</para>
                        <talk>A third option is to automatically build and deploy a static site on a regular basis. This
                            allows content to be managed in a collaborative environment, such as SVN, Wiki or (my mind
                            is blank, what&apos;s MS&apos; version control). Content developers and editors can
                            monitor change notifications in order to ensure no errors or innapropriate content is added.
                            If they take no action all changes will be made to the live server by the "ForrestBot" (an
                            automated publishing application) after a given time period.</talk>
                    </item>
                </bulletList>
                <addlInfo title="Delivery of Content">
                    <para>Unique amongst comparable documentation tools, Forrest generates sites that can run both
                        interactively as a dynamic web application, or as statically rendered pages.</para>
                    <para>This is important since some publication formats are static by their nature, for example
                        printed materials will always be static. However, the ability to serve in a dynamic environment
                        enables realtime updating of sites when content is edited (including otherwise static documents,
                        such as PDF). Furthermore, it provides a path for website growth: start off small and static,
                        and if dynamic features (user login, forms processing, runtime data, site search etc) are one
                        day needed, these can be accommodated by switching to webapp mode.</para>
                </addlInfo>
            </page>
        </chapter>
        <chapter title="SSP Power in Detail">
            <page title="Single Source Publishing XXL">
                <para>Internally Forrest implements SSP in a 21st century software architecture:</para>
                <talk>In the next section we&apos;ll talk about ...</talk>
                <bulletList>
                    <item>Modular architecture with a flexible plugin concept</item>
                    <item>
                        <para>Separate presentation layer and separation of concerns</para>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <para>Commitment to platform independence and common standards</para>
                    </item>
                </bulletList>
                <chapterTOC />
            </page>
            <page title="Extensibility through PlugIns">
                <comment>Show the first figure again and show the plugins in it while explaining the roles of plugins.
                    If possible we&apos;ll have an embedded forrest in the page to show the features </comment>
                <demo>Ross brings up the diagramm and fso shows three types of plugins in the diagram.</demo>
                <bulletList>
                    <item>Input-plugins to make use of files in many common data formats.</item>
                    <item>Output-plugins to present your content in various common formats.</item>
                    <item>Extend functionality with internal plugins to meet authors needs.</item>
                </bulletList>
                <addlInfo title="Extensibility">
                    <para>Forrest, at its core, is nothing more than a framework for processing XML documents. However,
                        it has a plugin mechanism that allows features to be added by simply installing any number of
                        plugins. Plugins are installed simply by adding their name to your projects configuration.</para>
                    <para>There are three types of plugin:</para>
                    <bulletList>
                        <item>
                            <para>Input Plugins<br /> These read in a file of a specific format, for example, Docbook or
                                MS Office and convert them to a format usable by Apache Forrest</para>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <para>Output Plugins<br /> These take the processed files output by Forrest core and convert
                                them into some rendered format. For example XHTML, PDF or plain Text.</para>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <para>Internal Plugins<br /> Extend the internal processing of the data. Internal plugins
                                perform functions like building site navigation structures.</para>
                        </item>
                    </bulletList>
                    <para>The functionality of Apache Forrest can be extended almost limitlessly. The project maintains
                        a list of Plugins (<xref url="http://wforrest.apache.org">Apache Forrest website
                            (http://wforrest.apache.org)</xref>) that have been complete or are in development. We are
                        also aware of projects that have built plugins to do things such as execute database queries,
                        read electronic sensors and perform periodic updates of sections of the content.</para>
                    <para>Note: Plugins are a new feature of the most recent release of Forrest. The project is
                        currently extracting functionality from the core into plugins in order to enable users to build
                        the document publishing system that satisfies their individual needs. However, this is an
                        ongoing process and at the time of writing some functionality scheduled to be moved into plugins
                        still remains in core. This simply means that you may have some features you don&apos;t need
                        as part of your initial download.</para>
                </addlInfo>
            </page>
            <page title="Skinnable Interface">
                <para>Forrest&apos;s keeps site design separate from content (separation of concerns)</para>
                <bulletList>
                    <item>Content authors don&apos;t have to worry about looks:
                            <code><![CDATA[ <skill level="advanced, BSc">Internet Technologies</skill> ]]></code>
                    </item>
                    <item>Designers develop and test new looks without interfering with content creation.</item>
                    <item>New skins can be applied to all documents in a flash. <demo>Show screenshots of skins and
                            sites</demo>
                    </item>
                </bulletList>
                <addlInfo title="Real Life Skinning Applications">
                    <para>Output formats can be "skinned" that is, the look and feel can be changed quickly and easily.
                        As with plugins. The skins are external units of functionality and can be packaged and
                        downloaded as and when needed. Alternatively, users can develop their own skins consistent with
                        corporate branding.</para>
                    <section title="Some Example Skins Developed By Forrest Users">
                        <section title="http://www.verit.de/">
                            <image id="skinShots1" url="images/skin_verit.gif" alternativeText="verit skin" />
                        </section>
                        <section title="http://www.xmlbelux.be/">
                            <image id="skinShots2" url="images/skin_xmlbelux.gif" alternativeText="XML Belux
                                skin" />
                        </section>
                        <section title="http://www.dream-models.com">
                            <image id="skinShots3" url="images/skin_dream_models.gif" alternativeText="Dream
                                Models skin" />
                        </section>
                        <section title="http://www.outerthought.net">
                            <image id="skinShots4" url="images/skin_outerthought.gif" alternativeText="Outerthought
                                skin" />
                        </section>
                        <section title="http://cese.sourceforge.net">
                            <image id="skinShots5" url="images/skin_cese.gif" alternativeText="CESE skin" />
                        </section>
                    </section>
                </addlInfo>
            </page>
        </chapter>
        <chapter title="Forrest for (Your) Business">
            <page title="Making the most of Forrest and SSP ...">
                <para>A few tips for a good start:</para>
                <chapterTOC />
            </page>
            <page title="Forrest Licensing" listIn="chapterTOC">
                <comment>skip this slide if running out of time.</comment>
                <para>What does the Apache License mean?</para>
                <bulletList>
                    <item>You can use the Forrest free of charge! <talk>Great!</talk>
                    </item>
                    <item>It is OK to use for commercial projects (with very few limitations). </item>
                    <item>Your extensions and modifications will not have to become Open Source.</item>
                    <item>
                        <para>You could even create new commercial Software based on Forrest. </para>
                        <talk>Even better!</talk>
                    </item>
                </bulletList>
                <talk>
                    <para>You get Forrest &apos;as is&apos; There are no guarantees!<br /> This needs a closer
                        look!</para>
                </talk>
                <addlInfo title="Apache Software License (Version 2.0)">
                    <para>
                        <xref url="http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0"
                            >http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0</xref> (TXT or HTML)</para>
                    <para>The 2.0 version of the Apache License was approved by the ASF in 2004. The goals of this
                        license revision have been to reduce the number of frequently asked questions, to allow the
                        license to be reusable without modification by any project (including non-ASF projects), to
                        allow the license to be included by reference instead of listed in every file, to clarify the
                        license on submission of contributions, to require a patent license on contributions that
                        necessarily infringe the contributor&apos;s own patents, and to move comments regarding
                        Apache and other inherited attribution notices to a location outside the license terms (the
                        NOTICE file).</para>
                    <para>The result is a license that is supposed to be compatible with other open source licenses
                        while remaining true to the original goals of the Apache Group and supportive of collaborative
                        development across both nonprofit and commercial organizations. The Apache Software Foundation
                        is still trying to determine if this version of the Apache License is compatible with the GPL.</para>
                    <para>All packages produced by the ASF are implicitly licensed under the Apache License, Version
                        2.0, unless otherwise explicitly stated. More developer documentation on how to apply the Apache
                        License to your work can be found in Applying the Apache License, Version 2.0.</para>
                </addlInfo>
            </page>
            <page title="Rules of Open Source" listIn="chapterTOC">
                <heading>Rules of Open Source</heading>
                <comment>skip this slide if running out of time.</comment>
                <para>As Open Source development is a volunteer effort, it follows other rules than Closed Source
                    Software:</para>
                <bulletList>
                    <item>You are free to use what is already there ...<bulletList>
                            <item>and welcome to add what is missing,</item>
                            <item>or spend some money (saved on the license) to have someone else add it for you.</item>
                        </bulletList>
                    </item>
                </bulletList>
                <bulletList>
                    <item>Forrest - just like Slosed Source Software - has bugs ... <bulletList>
                            <item>but we are committed to fixing them,</item>
                            <item>and have no sales department to push us into hasty releases.</item>
                        </bulletList>
                    </item>
                </bulletList>
            </page>
            <page title="Getting Bug Fixes and Support" listIn="chapterTOC">
                <heading>Getting Bug Fixes and Support</heading>
                <bulletList>
                    <item>
                        <para>There is no Forrest hotline ...</para>
                        <bulletList>
                            <item>
                                <para>but a mailing lists (<xref url="http://forrest.apache.org/mail-lists.html"
                                        >http://forrest.apache.org/mail-lists.html</xref>) to address any question You
                                    have about Forrest,</para>
                            </item>
                            <item> to discuss Your questions with the people who build forrest ,</item>
                            <item>and a large helpful community.</item>
                        </bulletList>
                    </item>
                </bulletList>
                <bulletList>
                    <item>
                        <para>If a bug is bugging you ...</para>
                        <bulletList>
                            <item>do something about it: help us fix it ... </item>
                            <item>and you will find a lot of people chipping in.</item>
                        </bulletList>
                    </item>
                </bulletList>
                <addlInfo title="Contributing">
                    <para> The Forrest Project is an <xref url="http://www.opensource.org/">Open Source
                            (http://www.opensource.org/)</xref> volunteer project released under a very liberal license.
                        This means there are many ways to contribute to the project - either with direct participation
                        (coding, documenting, answering questions, proposing ideas, reporting bugs, suggesting
                        bug-fixes, etc..) or by resource donations (money, time, publicity, hardware, software,
                        conference presentations, speeches, etc...). </para>
                    <para> To begin with, we suggest you to subscribe to the Forrest mailing lists (<xref
                            url="http://forrest.apache.org/mail-lists.html"
                        >http://forrest.apache.org/mail-lists.html</xref>) (follow the link for information on how to
                        subscribe and to access the mail list archives). Listen-in for a while, to hear how others make
                        contributions. </para>
                    <para>You can get your local working copy of the <xref
                            url="http://svn.apache.org/viewcvs.cgi/forrest/trunk/">latest and greatest code</xref>
                        (which you find in the Forrest module in the SVN code repository. Review the todo list, choose a
                        task (or perhaps you have noticed something that needs patching). Make the changes, do the
                        testing, generate a patch, and post to the developer mailing list. (Do not worry - the process
                        is easy and explained on the Forrest website.) </para>
                    <para> Document writers are usually the most wanted people so if you like to help but
                        you&apos;re not familiar with the innermost technical details, don&apos;t worry: we have
                        work for you! </para>
                    <bulletList>
                        <item>
                            <para>
                                <xref url="http://www.apache.org/foundation/how-it-works.html">How The Apache Software
                                    Foundation Works (http://www.apache.org/foundation/how-it-works.html)</xref>
                            </para>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <para>
                                <xref url="http://forrest.apache.org/contrib.html">Contributing to Forrest
                                    (http://forrest.apache.org/contrib.html)</xref>
                            </para>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <para>
                                <xref url="http://forrest.apache.org/mail-lists.html">Forrest mailing lists
                                    (http://forrest.apache.org/mail-lists.html)</xref>
                            </para>
                        </item>
                    </bulletList>
                </addlInfo>
            </page>
            <page title="Is Forrest a Reliable Platform?" listIn="chapterTOC">
                <heading>A reliable platform?</heading>
                <para>Trust Forrest with mission critical business applications if you follow a few simple rules:</para>
                <bulletList>
                    <item>
                        <para>Plan to spend some of the license fees saved</para>
                        <talk>to fix bugs or add features.</talk>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <para>Don&apos;t assume that <strong>O</strong>pen <strong>S</strong>ource
                            <strong>S</strong>oftware is easier to learn.</para>
                        <talk>Spend money on proper training</talk>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <para>Take your time introducing Forrest.</para>
                        <talk>
                            <para>to get to know Forrest and determine if the current version will suit your needs.
                                <br />Talk about current version numbers</para>
                        </talk>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <para>Help us make Forrest better.</para>
                        <talk>
                            <para>there are many ways to contribute ...<br />We are looking for CSS experts!</para>
                        </talk>
                    </item>
                </bulletList>
            </page>
        </chapter>
        <page title="Conclusion">
            <heading>Thank You!</heading>
            <talk>
                <para>This concludes our presentation<br /> Thanks for your time. We&apos;ll now take Your
                    questions.</para>
            </talk>
            <bulletList>
                <item>Presentation</item>
                <item>
                    <para><strong>Questions &amp; Answers</strong> (20 min)</para>
                </item>
            </bulletList>
        </page>
        <page title="Time for Questions">
            <heading>Time for Your Questions</heading>
            <para>We have only 10 minutes</para>
            <bulletList>
                <item>Try to keep it short</item>
                <item>Give others a chance to ask there questions</item>
            </bulletList>
            <para>For further information check out:</para>
            <bulletList>
                <item>
                    <para>
                        <xref url="http://forrest.apache.org">http://forrest.apache.org</xref>
                    </para>
                </item>
                <item>
                    <para>
                        <xref url="http://forrest.apache.org/mail-lists.html"
                        >http://forrest.apache.org/mail-lists.html</xref>
                    </para>
                </item>
            </bulletList>
        </page>
        <page title="leftovers" showOnlyFor="slides">
            <heading>Forrest Configurations</heading>
            <para>The default behaviour of Forrest is to publish to the web and to print. However, an increasing range
                of extensions are making it possible to publish to other media, such as Eclipse Help files or RSS. We
                will discuss these extensions later. </para>
            <para />
        </page>
    </content>
</presentation>
