<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  Copyright 2002-2004 The Apache Software Foundation or its licensors,
  as applicable.

  Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
  you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  You may obtain a copy of the License at

      http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.
-->
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN" "http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">
<document> 
  <header> 
    <title>Welcome to the org.apache.forrest.plugin.input.Daisy Plugin</title> 
  </header> 
  <body> 
    <section>
      <title>Apache Forrest - org.apache.forrest.plugin.input.Daisy Plugin</title>
      <p>This plugin retrieves documents from a 
      <a href="http://www.cocoondev.org/daisy">Daisy</a>
      repository.</p>
    </section>
    
    <section>
      <title>Usage</title>
      
      <p>Perhaps the most important thing to realise about this plugin is that 
      there is no relationship between the Forrest URL space and the URL space
      defined in the Daisy repository. That is the path to and the name of each
      document within Forrest needs not be the same as the path to and the name
      of the document within the Daisy repository.</p>
      
      <p>This enables the repository to be structured in a way that is
      appropriate for it's editors and the Forrest document collection can
      be structured in a way that is appropriate for the target audience. In
      fact, it is possible to use the same document from a Daisy repository in
      multiple Forrest collections each using a completely different URL 
      space that is custom designed for the end user of the document
      collection.</p> 
      
      <p>In order to tell Forrest which document to retrieve from the
      repository you need to pass a number of request parameters in the URL.
      These are listed in the table below.</p>
      
      <table>
        <caption>Request Parameters</caption>
        <tr>
          <th>Parameter</th>
          <th>Comments</th>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <th>repositoryURL</th>
          <td>The URL of the Daisy-Wiki interface to the repository.</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <th>repositoryPort</th>
          <td>The Port number of the daisy-wiki application. If
          ommitted the default value of 80 is used.</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <th>repositoryCollection</th>
          <td>The name of the collection in which the document is stored.</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <th>documentID</th>
          <td>The ID of the document within Daisy. This can be the numeric
          identifier used by Daisy repository or it can be any valid ID as 
          defined within the Daisy-Wiki. The documentID can also define
          a version and/or variant of the document if required. This is done
          in exactly the same way as would be done in he Daisy-Wiki.</td>
        </tr>
      </table>
      
      <section>
        <title>Examples</title>
          <ul>
            <li><a href="daisy/index.html?repositoryURL=www.cocoondev.org&amp;repositoryCollection=daisy&amp;documentID=index">Daisy Home Page</a> (retrieved live, you must be online)</li>
          </ul>
      </section>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>