<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more
  contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file distributed with
  this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.
  The ASF licenses this file to You under the Apache License, Version 2.0
  (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with
  the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

      http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.
-->
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN" "http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">
<document>
  <header>
    <title>Upgrading to Apache Forrest 0.9</title>
  </header>
  <body>
    <section id="introduction">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>
        This page describes some changes to Apache Forrest that affect people
        who are upgrading to the 0.9 version. If you have other issues, then
        please discuss on either the
        <a href="site:mail-lists/forrest-dev">dev</a> or
        <a href="site:mail-lists/forrest-user">user</a> mailing lists. As more
        experience is gained, this document will be updated.
      </p>
      <p>
        (If you are upgrading from a version prior to 0.8 then you will need to
        see the notes for the previous upgrade.)
      </p>
    </section>
    <section id="new">
      <title>New Features</title>
      <p>
        The following list shows some of the key new features.
        See also the <code>RELEASE-NOTES</code> document that was provided with
        the release package. For the full list
        of changes, see the main <a href="site:changes">change log</a> and also
        for each plugin.
      </p>
      <ul>
        <li>
          Our packaged Apache Cocoon is upgraded, along with various other
          important supporting products such as Apache Xerces and Apache Xalan, etc.
        </li>
        <li>
          The properties are supplemented by the new
          <a href="site:properties">Properties</a> system.
        </li>
        <li>Java 1.5</li>
      </ul>
      <p>
        Some new initial plugins are in the "whiteboard". See the entries in the
        <a href="site:changes">change log</a> and see each plugin's
        documentation and changes log. This includes the new Dispatcher. See
        <a href="site:status-themes">Status of Themes: Skins and Dispatcher</a>.
      </p>
    </section>
    <section id="jdk15">
      <title>Java 1.5 (or newer) is required</title>
      <p>
        Java 1.5 (or newer) is required, starting with this Forrest 0.9 version.
        For further information, see
        <a href="site:v0.90//faq/requirements">FAQ</a>.
      </p>
    </section>
    <section id="cocoon">
      <title>Notes about Cocoon version</title>
      <p>
        Our packaged version of Apache Cocoon has been upgraded to use the
        latest version of their stable 2.1 branch. This is a major step forward
        for Forrest. It enables us to use a reliable and up-to-date Cocoon.
        Forrest developers can again participate at Cocoon to fix issues or
        develop new blocks. A number of major performance issues are already
        fixed in this version.
      </p>
      <p>
        In previous versions of Forrest we were using a development version of
        Cocoon trunk (i.e. 2.2). A number of things happened which caused us to
        fall out of synchronisation with Cocoon. They started using Maven as a
        build system, which took a long time to settle down. In turn that meant
        that Apache Gump could not perform continuous integration, which shut
        Forrest off. At the same time Cocoon trunk was making technical advances
        which changed some of the ways that Forrest interacts with Cocoon. In
        particular the command-line interface which Forrest uses to build a
        complete static site.
        See other notes via <a href="http://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/FOR-1017">FOR-1017</a>.
      </p>
      <p>
        Cocoon-2.1 is closer to our stalled version of Cocoon-2.2 than the
        current head of Cocoon-2.2 trunk.
      </p>
      <p>
        Note that this move does not preclude us from future updates to other
        versions of Cocoon or even to another xml processing framework.
      </p>
      <p>
        If you want to use your own version of Cocoon-2.1, for example to add
        another Cocoon Block or to enhance a particular existing block, then
        see the notes in the <code>$FORREST_HOME/etc/cocoon_upgrade</code>
        directory.
      </p>

      <section id="cocoon-upgrade">
        <title>Cocoon upgrade issues</title>
        <p>
          There are only two minor issues for those upgrading from the previous
          version of Forrest:
        </p>
        <p>
          When you first use this in your existing projects, there will probably
          be a message about a certain cache item. On the second run all is well.
          A way to avoid that would be to do 'forrest clean-work' in each of
          your projects to remove the old Cocoon cache.
        </p>
        <p>
          The configuration file is now at
          <code>main/webapp/WEB-INF/cocoon.xconf</code>
        </p>
        <p>
          Our previous version of Cocoon had a facility called "Running modes"
          which enabled one set of a minimal group of properties for development
          and a different set for production. This is not available in Cocoon-2.1
          version. If you were using this feature, then simply move your defined
          properties into the <code>main/webapp/WEB-INF/properties/core.properties</code>
          file.
        </p>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section id="missing-symbols">
      <title>Missing project symbols file in some projects</title>
      <p>Users of 0.8, and developers with older 0.9-dev, who based their sites on 'forrest seed-basic' rather than 'forrest seed-sample' will be affected by <a href="https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/FOR-1075">FOR-1075</a>. There was a partially implemented xml catalog with missing symbols file.
      </p>
      <p>
        You would get the message:
      </p>
      <source>Failed to create InputSource (java.io.FileNotFoundException:
.../src/documentation/resources/schema/symbols-project-v10.ent
(No such file or directory)...</source>
      <p>
        This is just a warning message from the misconfigured xml entity catalog.
        To silence it, simply copy the file from a new "seed-basic" site,
        or more directly by
        <code>cp $FORREST_HOME/main/fresh-site/src/documentation/resources/schema/symbols-project-v10.ent $PROJECT/src/documentation/resources/schema/symbols-project-v10.ent</code>
      </p>
      <p>
        This "project symbols" ability using xml entities is useful in two ways.
        To provide common symbols, words, and phrases, in your source documents
        (added in v0.8 - <a href="site:faq/xml-entities">FAQ</a>).
        To configure some Cocoon sitemap components
        (added in v0.9 - <a href="site:faq/sitemap-entities">FAQ</a>).
      </p>
    </section>
    <section id="pdf">
      <title>Improved PDF output plugin</title>
      <p>
        Many plugins have been upgraded and there are some new plugins.
        See the <a href="site:changes">Changes</a> and the <a href="site:pluginVersions/overview">Plugins</a>
        documentation.
      </p>
      <p>
        In particular, the PDF output plugin has many improvements, uses a newer Apache FOP etc.
        It is much more configurable, See its plugin documentation.
      </p>
      <p>
        However there is a minor, but annoying, problem.
        See <a href="https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/FOR-1077">FOR-1077</a>.
        Forrest (via Cocoon) re-generates every document. Every PDF now gets differences
        due to some internal metadata dates, even though its content might not have changed.
        When the documentation set is deployed, e.g. via svn, these changed files will also
        be deployed.
      </p>
      <p>
        For the Forrest project website, we decided to stop (via skinconf.xml) using PDFs
        for every page and do it only for some specific documents.
      </p>
      <p>
        Remember that if you need to use an old version of any plugin, then it can be
        specified in forrest.properties by appending the version number (e.g. "-0.2" or "-0.3")
        to the required plugin name.
      </p>
    </section>
    <section id="generated-id">
      <title>Improved generated IDs for sections</title>
      <p>
        The conversion of xdoc sections to html will generate named anchors
        for use with URI fragment identifiers.
      </p>
      <p>
        Forrest utilises the @id attribute if it exists (ideal).
        Otherwise it generates one utilising the "section/title" element.
      </p>
      <p>
        With prior versions of Forrest, an extra automatic ID was always generated.
        This now only happens if those other pieces are missing.
      </p>
      <p>
        So when you first update your project's deployed html documentation, there will
        be many changes removing those old superfluous named anchors
        (e.g. <code>&lt;a name="N1000E"</code>).
      </p>
    </section>
    <section id="docs">
      <title>Notes about documentation</title>
      <p>
        After each release, the "Versioned Docs" are copied to form the new
        "dev" set. Ideally the docs are then upgraded in readiness for the new
        release. This has not been completed for recent releases. In particular
        there are example snippets of sitemaps which have not yet been upgraded
        to reflect the changes to the sitemaps and the separation of some core
        stuff into plugins. See issues
        <a href="https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/FOR-546">FOR-546</a> and
        <a href="https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/FOR-922">FOR-922</a> and
        others.
      </p>
    </section>
    <section id="tips">
      <title>General upgrade tips</title>
      <p>
        Synchronise your project's skinconf.xml and forrest.properties files:
      </p>
      <p>
        Take advantage of the separation of concerns. In a new workspace, create
        a fresh '<code>forrest seed</code>' site, then tweak its
        forrest.properties and skinconf.xml until it reflects your old site.
        When it is ready, replace your project's skinconf.xml and
        forrest.properties files. Any remaining issues would concern other
        aspects of your configuration, such as site.xml and your actual content.
      </p>
    </section>
    <section id="project-sitemap">
      <title>Remove project sitemap if not necessary</title>
      <p>
        It has come to our attention that some people have a
        <a href="site:project-sitemap">project sitemap</a>
        even though they are not using it. Such un-necessary sitemaps should be
        removed to avoid maintenance issues.
      </p>
      <p>
        If you do use a project sitemap, then pay attention to the 0.8 upgrade
        instructions "<a href="site:upgrading_08">Forrest configuration simplification</a>".
      </p>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>To be continued...</title>
      <p>
        ...as more issues are discovered/remembered :) Please send feedback to
        the <a href="site:mail-lists/forrest-dev">mailing list</a>.
      </p>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>
